<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI.2><text><body><div1 type="Book" n="2" org="uniform" sample="complete"><head><placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName></head><p>
<milestone n="1" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /></p><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />The Corinthian land is a portion of the <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName>, and is named after <placeName key="tgn,7010734" authname="tgn,7010734">Corinthus</placeName>. That <placeName key="tgn,7010734" authname="tgn,7010734">Corinthus</placeName> was a son of Zeus I have never known anybody say seriously except the majority of the Corinthians. Eumelus, the son of Amphilytus,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">8th cent. B.C.</note> of the family called Bacchidae, who is said to have composed the epic poem, says in his Corinthian History （if indeed the history be his） that <placeName key="perseus,Ephyra" authname="perseus,Ephyra">Ephyra</placeName>, the daughter of Oceanus, dwelt first in this land; that afterwards Marathon, the son of Epopeus, the son of Aloeus, the son of Helius （Sun）, fleeing from the lawless violence of his father migrated to the sea coast of <placeName key="tgn,7002681" authname="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>; that on the death of Epopeus he came to <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>, divided his kingdom among his sons, and returned to <placeName key="tgn,7002681" authname="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>; and that Asopia was renamed after <placeName key="tgn,7011098" authname="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName>, and Ephyraea after <placeName key="tgn,7010734" authname="tgn,7010734">Corinthus</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" /><placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> is no longer inhabited by any of the old Corinthians, but by colonists sent out by the Romans. This change is due to the Achaean League.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">A league of states in the northern <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>. It was most influential in the second half of the third century B.C. Founded <date value="-280" authname="-280">280 B.C.</date></note> The Corinthians, being members of it, joined in the war against the Romans, which Critolaus, when appointed general of the Achaeans, brought about by persuading to revolt both the Achaeans and the majority of the Greeks outside the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>. When the Romans won the war, they carried out a general disarmament of the Greeks<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><date value="-146" authname="-146">146 B.C.</date></note> and dismantled the walls of such cities as were fortified. <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> was laid waste by Mummius, who at that time commanded the Romans in the field, and it is said that it was afterwards refounded by Caesar,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><date value="-44" authname="-44">44 B.C.</date></note> who was the author of the present constitution of <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. <placeName key="perseus,Carthage" authname="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>, too, they say, was refounded in his reign.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>In the Corinthian territory is also the place called Cromyon from Cromus the son of Poseidon. Here they say that Phaea was bred; overcoming this sow was one of the traditional achievements of Theseus. Farther on the pine still grew by the shore at the time of my visit, and there was an altar of Melicertes. At this place, they say, the boy was brought ashore by a dolphin; Sisyphus found him lying and gave him burial on the Isthmus, establishing the Isthmian games in his honor.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>At the beginning of the Isthmus is the place where the brigand Sinis used to take hold of pine trees and draw them down. All those whom he overcame in fight he used to tie to the trees, and then allow them to swing up again. Thereupon each of the pines used to drag to itself the bound man, and as the bond gave way in neither direction but was stretched equally in both, he was torn in two. This was the way in which Sinis himself was slain by Theseus. For Theseus rid of evildoers the road from <placeName key="tgn,5004287" authname="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName> to <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, killing those whom I have enumerated and, in sacred <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName>, Periphetes, thought to be the son of Hephaestus, who used to fight with a bronze club.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>The Corinthian Isthmus stretches on the one hand to the sea at Cenchreae, and on the other to the sea at Lechaeum. For this is what makes the region to the south mainland. He who tried to make the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName> an island gave up before digging through the Isthmus. Where they began to dig is still to be seen, but into the rock they did not advance at all. So it still is mainland as its nature is to be. Alexander the son of Philip wished to dig through Mimas, and his attempt to do this was his only unsuccessful project. The Cnidians began to dig through their isthmus, but the Pythian priestess stopped them. So difficult it is for man to alter by violence what Heaven has made.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />A legend of the Corinthians about their land is not peculiar to them, for I believe that the Athenians were the first to relate a similar story to glorify <placeName key="tgn,7002681" authname="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>. The Corinthians say that Poseidon had a dispute with Helius （Sun） about the land, and that Briareos arbitrated between them, assigning to Poseidon the Isthmus and the parts adjoining, and giving to Helius the height above the city.<milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Ever since, they say, the Isthmus has belonged to Poseidon.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>Worth seeing here are a theater and a white-marble race-course. Within the sanctuary of the god stand on the one side portrait statues of athletes who have won victories at the Isthmian games, on the other side pine trees growing in a row, the greater number of them rising up straight. On the temple, which is not very large, stand bronze Tritons. In the fore-temple are images, two of Poseidon, a third of Amphitrite, and a Sea, which also is of bronze. The offerings inside were dedicated in our time by Herodes the Athenian, four horses, gilded except for the hoofs, which are of ivory,</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p>and two gold Tritons beside the horses, with the parts below the waist of ivory. On the car stand Amphitrite and Poseidon, and there is the boy Palaemon upright upon a dolphin. These too are made of ivory and gold. On the middle of the base on which the car is has been wrought a Sea holding up the young Aphrodite, and on either side are the nymphs called Nereids. I know that there are altars to these in other parts of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, and that some Greeks have even dedicated to them precincts by shores, where honors are also paid to Achilles. In Gabala is a holy sanctuary of Doto, where there was still remaining the robe by which the Greeks say that Eriphyle was bribed to wrong her son Alcmaeon.</p>
<milestone n="9" unit="section" /><p>Among the reliefs on the base of the statue of Poseidon are the sons of Tyndareus, because these too are saviours of ships and of sea-faring men. The other offerings are images of Calm and of Sea, a horse like a whale from the breast onward, Ino and Bellerophontes, and the horse Pegasus.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Within the enclosure is on the left a temple of Palaemon, with images in it of Poseidon, Leucothea and Palaemon himself. There is also what is called his Holy of Holies, and an underground descent to it, where they say that Palaemon is concealed. Whosoever, whether Corinthian or stranger, swears falsely here, can by no means escape from his oath. There is also an ancient sanctuary called the altar of the Cyclopes, and they sacrifice to the Cyclopes upon it.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>The graves of Sisyphus and of Neleus—for they say that Neleus came to <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, died of disease, and was buried near the Isthmus—I do not think that anyone would look for after reading Eumelus. For he says that not even to Nestor did Sisyphus show the tomb of Neleus, because it must be kept unknown to everybody alike, and that Sisyphus is indeed buried on the Isthmus, but that few Corinthians, even those of his own day, knew where the grave was. The Isthmian games were not interrupted even when <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> had been laid waste by Mummius, but so long as it lay deserted the celebration of the games was entrusted to the Sicyonians, and when it was rebuilt the honor was restored to the present inhabitants.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />The names of the Corinthian harbors were given them by Leches and Cenchrias, said to be the children of Poseidon and Peirene the daughter of Achelous, though in the poem called <title>The Great Eoeae</title><note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Said to be a work of Hesiod.</note> Peirene is said to be a daughter of Oebalus. In Lechaeum are a sanctuary and a bronze image of Poseidon, and on the road leading from the Isthmus to Cenchreae a temple and ancient wooden image of Artemis. In Cenchreae are a temple and a stone statue of Aphrodite, after it on the mole running into the sea a bronze image of Poseidon, and at the other end of the harbor sanctuaries of Asclepius and of Isis. Right opposite Cenchreae is Helen's Bath. It is a large stream of salt, tepid water, flowing from a rock into the sea.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>As one goes up to <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> are tombs, and by the gate is buried Diogenes<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The “Cynic” philosopher</note> of Sinope, whom the Greeks surname the Dog. Before the city is a grove of cypresses called Craneum. Here are a precinct of Bellerophontes, a temple of Aphrodite Melaenis and the grave of Lais, upon which is set a lioness holding a ram in her fore-paws.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />There is in <placeName key="tgn,7001399" authname="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName> another tomb which claims to be that of Lais, for she went to that country also when she fell in love with Hippostratus. The story is that originally she was of Hycara in <placeName key="tgn,7003122" authname="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>. Taken captive while yet a girl by Nicias and the Athenians, she was sold and brought to <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, where she surpassed in beauty the courtesans of her time, and so won the admiration of the Corinthians that even now they claim Lais as their own.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>The things worthy of mention in the city include the extant remains of antiquity, but the greater number of them belong to the period of its second ascendancy. On the market-place, where most of the sanctuaries are, stand Artemis surnamed Ephesian and wooden images of Dionysus, which are covered with gold with the exception of their faces; these are ornamented with red paint. They are called Lysius and Baccheus,</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>and I too give the story told about them. They say that Pentheus treated Dionysus despitefully, his crowning outrage being that he went to Cithaeron, to spy upon the women, and climbing up a tree beheld what was done. When the women detected Pentheus, they immediately dragged him down, and joined in tearing him, living as he was, limb from limb. Afterwards, as the Corinthians say, the Pythian priestess commanded them by an oracle to discover that tree and to worship it equally with the god. For this reason they have made these images from the tree.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />There is also a temple of Fortune, with a standing image of Parian marble. Beside it is a sanctuary for all the gods. Hard by is built a fountain, on which is a bronze Poseidon; under the feet of Poseidon is a dolphin spouting water. There is also a bronze Apollo surnamed Clarius and a statue of Aphrodite made by Hermogenes of <placeName key="tgn,7010869" authname="tgn,7010869">Cythera</placeName>. There are two bronze, standing images of Hermes, for one of which a temple has been made. The images of Zeus also are in the open; one had not a surname, another they call Chthonius （of the Lower World） and the third Most High.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />In the middle of the market-place is a bronze Athena, on the pedestal of which are wrought in relief figures of the Muses. Above the market-place is a temple of Octavia the sister of Augustus, who was emperor of the Romans after Caesar, the founder of the modern <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>On leaving the market-place along the road to Lechaeum you come to a gateway, on which are two gilded chariots, one carrying Phaethon the son of Helius （Sun）, the other Helius himself. A little farther away from the gateway, on the right as you go in, is a bronze Heracles. After this is the entrance to the water of Peirene. The legend about Peirene is that she was a woman who became a spring because of her tears shed in lamentation for her son Cenchrias, who was unintentionally killed by Artemis.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />The spring is ornamented with white marble, and there have been made chambers like caves, out of which the water flows into an open-air well. It Is pleasant to drink, and they say that the Corinthian bronze, when red-hot, is tempered by this water, since bronze . . . the Corinthians have not. Moreover near Peirene are an image and a sacred enclosure of Apollo; in the latter is a painting of the exploit of Odysseus against the suitors.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Proceeding on the direct road to Lechaeum we see a bronze image of a seated Hermes. By him stands a ram, for Hermes is the god who is thought most to care for and to increase flocks, as Homer puts it in the <title>Iliad</title>:—<quote type="verse"><l met="dact">Son was he of Phorbas, the dearest of Trojans to Hermes,</l><l>Rich in flocks, for the god vouchsafed him wealth in abundance.</l></quote><bibl n="Hom. Il. 14.490" default="NO" valid="yes">Hom. Il. 14.490</bibl>The story told at the mysteries of the Mother about Hermes and the ram I know but do not relate. After the image of Hermes come Poseidon, Leucothea, and Palaemon on a dolphin.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>The Corinthians have baths in many parts of the city, some put up at the public charge and one by the emperor Hadrian. The most famous of them is near the Poseidon. It was made by the Spartan Eurycles,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Probably a contemporary of Augustus.</note> who beautified it with various kinds of stone, especially the one quarried at Croceae in <placeName key="tgn,7002745" authname="tgn,7002745">Laconia</placeName>. On the left of the entrance stands a Poseidon, and after him Artemis hunting. Throughout the city are many wells, for the Corinthians have a copious supply of flowing water, besides the water which the emperor Hadrian brought from Lake Stymphalus, but the most noteworthy is the one by the side of the image of Artemis. Over it is a Bellerophontes, and the water flows through the hoof of the horse Pegasus.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>As you go along another road from the market-place, which leads to <placeName key="tgn,7011098" authname="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName>, you can see on the right of the road a temple and bronze image of Apollo, and a little farther on a well called the Well of Glauce. Into this they say she threw herself in the belief that the water would be a cure for the drugs of Medea. Above this well has been built what is called the Odeum （Music Hall）, beside which is the tomb of Medea's children. Their names were Mermerus and Pheres, and they are said to have been stoned to death by the Corinthians owing to the gifts which legend says they brought to Glauce.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>But as their death was violent and illegal, the young babies of the Corinthians were destroyed by them until, at the command of the oracle, yearly sacrifices were established in their honor and a figure of Terror was set up. This figure still exists, being the likeness of a woman frightful to look upon but after <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> was laid waste by the Romans and the old Corinthians were wiped out, the new settlers broke the custom of offering those sacrifices to the sons of Medea, nor do their children cut their hair for them or wear black clothes.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p>On the occasion referred to Medea went to <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and married Aegeus, but subsequently she was detected plotting against Theseus and fled from <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> also; coming to the land then called <placeName key="tgn,7002243" authname="tgn,7002243">Aria</placeName> she caused its inhabitants to be named after her Medes. The son, whom she brought with her in her flight to the Arii, they say she had by Aegeus, and that his name was Medus. Hellanicus,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">A writer of the fifth century B.C.</note> however, calls him Polyxenus and says that his father was Jason.</p>
<milestone n="9" unit="section" /><p>The Greeks have an epic poem called <title>Naupactia</title>. In this Jason is represented as having removed his home after the death of Pelias from Iolcus to <placeName key="tgn,7010886" authname="tgn,7010886">Corcyra</placeName>, and Mermerus, the elder of his children, to have been killed by a lioness while hunting on the mainland opposite. Of Pheres is recorded nothing. But Cinaethon<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">An early epic writer.</note> of <placeName key="tgn,7011065" authname="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName>, another writer of pedigrees in verse, said that Jason's children by Medea were a son Medeus and a daughter Eriopis; he too, however, gives no further information about these children.</p>
<milestone n="10" unit="section" /><p>Eumelus said that Helius （Sun） gave the Asopian land to Aloeus and Epliyraea to Aeetes. When Aeetes was departing for <placeName key="tgn,7016642" authname="tgn,7016642">Colchis</placeName> he entrusted his land to Bunus, the son of Hermes and Alcidamea, and when Bunus died Epopeus the son of Aloeus extended his kingdom to include the Ephyraeans. Afterwards, when <placeName key="tgn,7010734" authname="tgn,7010734">Corinthus</placeName>, the son of Marathon, died childless, the Corinthians sent for Medea from Iolcus and bestowed upon her the kingdom.</p>
<milestone n="11" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Through her Jason was king in <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, and Medea, as her children were born, carried each to the sanctuary of Hera and concealed them, doing so in the belief that so they would be immortal. At last she learned that her hopes were vain, and at the same time she was detected by Jason. When she begged for pardon he refused it, and sailed away to Iolcus. For these reasons Medea too departed, and handed over the kingdom to Sisyphus.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />This is the account that I read, and not far from the tomb is the temple of Athena Chalinitis （Bridler）. For Athena, they say, was the divinity who gave most help to Bellerophontes, and she delivered to him Pegasus, having herself broken in and bridled him. The image of her is of wood, but face, hands and feet are of white marble.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>That Bellerophontes was not an absolute king, but was subject to Proetus and the Argives is the belief of myself and of all who have read carefully the Homeric poems.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 6.159" default="NO" valid="yes">Hom. Il. 6.159</bibl></note> When Bellerophontes migrated to <placeName key="tgn,7001294" authname="tgn,7001294">Lycia</placeName> it is clear that the Corinthians none the less were subject to the despots at <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> or <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName>. By themselves they provided no leader for the campaign against <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, but shared in the expedition as part of the forces, Mycenaean and other, led by Agamemnon.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>Sisyphus had other sons besides Glaucus, the father of Bellerophontes a second was Ornytion, and besides him there were Thersander and <placeName key="tgn,1085963" authname="tgn,1085963">Almus</placeName>. Ornytion had a son Phocus, reputed to have been begotten by Poseidon. He migrated to <placeName key="perseus,Tithorea" authname="perseus,Tithorea">Tithorea</placeName> in what is now called Phocis, but Thoas, the younger son of Ornytion, remained behind at <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>. Thoas begat Damophon, Damophon begat Propodas, and Propodas begat Doridas and Hyanthidas. While these were kings the Dorians took the field against <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, their leader being Aletes, the son of Hippotas, the son of Phylas, the son of Antiochus, the son of Heracles. So Doridas and Hyanthidas gave up the kingship to Aletes and remained at <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, but the Corinthian people were conquered in battle and expelled by the Dorians.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>Aletes himself and his descendants reigned for five generations to Bacchis, the son of Prumnis, and, named after him, the Bacchidae reigned for five more generations to Telestes, the son of Aristodemus. Telestes was killed in hate by Arieus and Perantas, and there were no more kings, but Prytanes （Presidents） taken from the Bacchidae and ruling for one year, until Cypselus, the son of Eetion, became tyrant and expelled the Bacchidae.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><date value="-655" authname="-655">655 B.C.</date></note> Cypselus was a descendant of <placeName key="tgn,7002371" authname="tgn,7002371">Melas</placeName>, the son of Antasus. <placeName key="tgn,7002371" authname="tgn,7002371">Melas</placeName> from <placeName key="perseus,Gonussa" authname="perseus,Gonussa">Gonussa</placeName> above <placeName key="tgn,7011104" authname="tgn,7011104">Sicyon</placeName> joined the Dorians in the expedition against <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>. When the god expressed disapproval Aletes at first ordered <placeName key="tgn,7002371" authname="tgn,7002371">Melas</placeName> to withdraw to other Greeks, but afterwards, mistaking the oracle, he received him as a settler.<milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Such I found to be the history of the Corinthian kings.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>Now the sanctuary of Athena Chalinitis is by their theater, and near is a naked wooden image of Heracles, said to be a work of Daedalus. All the works of this artist, although rather uncouth to look at, are nevertheless distinguished by a kind of inspiration. Above the theater is a sanctuary of Zeus surnamed in the Latin tongue Capitolinus, which might be rendered into Greek “Coryphaeos”. Not far from this theater is the ancient gymnasium, and a spring called <placeName key="perseus,Lerna" authname="perseus,Lerna">Lerna</placeName>. Pillars stand around it, and seats have been made to refresh in summer time those who have entered it. By this gymnasium are temples of Zeus and Asclepius. The images of Asclepius and of Health are of white marble, that of Zeus is of bronze.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>The Acrocorinthus is a mountain peak above the city, assigned to Helius by Briareos when he acted as adjudicator, and handed over, the Corinthians say, by Helius to Aphrodite. As you go up this Acrocorinthus you see two precincts of Isis, one if Isis surnamed Pelagian （Marine） and the other of Egyptian Isis, and two of Serapis, one of them being of Serapis called “in <placeName key="tgn,1001079" authname="tgn,1001079">Canopus</placeName>.” After these are altars to Helius, and a sanctuary of Necessity and Force, into which it is not customary to enter.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Above it are a temple of the Mother of the gods and a throne; the image and the throne are made of stone. The temple of the Fates and that of Demeter and the Maid have images that are not exposed to view. Here, too, is the temple of Hera Bunaea set up by Bunus the son of Hermes. It is for this reason that the goddess is called Bunaea.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />On the summit of the Acrocorinthus is a temple of Aphrodite. The images are Aphrodite armed, Helius, and Eros with a bow. The spring, which is behind the temple, they say was the gift of Asopus to Sisyphus. The latter knew, so runs the legend, that Zeus had ravished <placeName key="tgn,7011087" authname="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName>, the daughter of Asopus, but refused to give information to the seeker before he had a spring given him on the Acrocorinthus. When Asopus granted this request Sisyphus turned informer, and on this account he receives—if anyone believes the story—punishment in Hades.  I have heard people say that this spring and Peirene are the same, the water in the city flowing hence under-ground.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>This Asopus rises in the Phliasian territory, flows through the Sicyonian, and empties itself into the sea here. His daughters, say the Phliasians, were <placeName key="tgn,7010886" authname="tgn,7010886">Corcyra</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,7011087" authname="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName>, and Thebe. <placeName key="tgn,7010886" authname="tgn,7010886">Corcyra</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7011087" authname="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName> gave new names to the islands called <placeName key="tgn,7010886" authname="tgn,7010886">Scheria</placeName> and Oenone, while from Thebe is named the city below the Cadmea. The Thebans do not agree, but say that Thebe was the daughter of the Boeotian, and not of the Phliasian, Asopus.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>The other stories about the river are current among both the Phliasians and the Sicyonians, for instance that its water is foreign and not native, in that the <placeName key="tgn,1121561" authname="tgn,1121561">Maeander</placeName>, descending from Celaenae through <placeName key="tgn,7002613" authname="tgn,7002613">Phrygia</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7002358" authname="tgn,7002358">Caria</placeName>, and emptying itself into the sea at <placeName key="perseus,Miletus" authname="perseus,Miletus">Miletus</placeName>, goes to the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName> and forms the Asopus. I remember hearing a similar story from the Delians, that the stream which they call Inopus comes to them from the <placeName key="tgn,1127805" authname="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName>. Further, there is a story that the <placeName key="tgn,1127805" authname="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName> itself is the <placeName key="tgn,1123842" authname="tgn,1123842">Euphrates</placeName>, which disappears into a marsh, rises again beyond Aethiopia and becomes the <placeName key="tgn,1127805" authname="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>Such is the account I heard of the Asopus. When you have turned from the Acrocorinthus into the mountain road you see the Teneatic gate and a sanctuary of Eilethyia. The town called <placeName key="perseus,Tenea" authname="perseus,Tenea">Tenea</placeName> is just about sixty stades distant. The inhabitants say that they are Trojans who were taken prisoners in <placeName key="perseus,Tenedos" authname="perseus,Tenedos">Tenedos</placeName> by the Greeks, and were permitted by Agamemnon to dwell in their present home. For this reason they honor Apollo more than any other god.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />As you go from <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, not into the interior but along the road to <placeName key="tgn,7011104" authname="tgn,7011104">Sicyon</placeName>, there is on the left not far from the city a burnt temple. There have, of course, been many wars carried on in Corinthian territory, and naturally houses and sanctuaries outside the wall have been fired. But this temple, they say, was Apollo's, and Pyrrhus the son of Achilles burned it down. Subsequently I heard another account, that the Corinthians built the temple for Olympian Zeus, and that suddenly fire from some quarter fell on it and destroyed it.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>The Sicyonians, the neighbours of the Corinthians at this part of the border, say about their own land that Aegialeus was its first and aboriginal inhabitant, that the district of the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName> still called Aegialus was named after him because he reigned over it, and that he founded the city Aegialea on the plain. Their citadel, they say, was where is now their sanctuary of Athena; further, that Aegialeus begat Europs, Europs Telchis, and Telchis Apis.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>This Apis reached such a height of power before Pelops came to <placeName key="perseus,Olympia" authname="perseus,Olympia">Olympia</placeName> that all the territory south of the Isthmus was called after him <placeName key="tgn,1099657" authname="tgn,1099657">Apia</placeName>. Apis begat Thelxion, Thelxion Aegyrus, the Thurimachus, and Thurimachus Leucippus. Leucippus had no male issue, only a daughter Calchinia. There is a story that this Calchinia mated with Poseidon; her child was reared by Leucippus, who at his death handed over to him the kingdom. His name was Peratus.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />What is reported of Plemnaeus, the son of Peratus, seemed to me very wonderful. All the children borne to him by his wife died the very first time they wailed. At last Demeter took pity on Plemnaeus, came to Aegialea in the guise of a strange woman, and reared for Plemnaeus his son Orthopolis. Orthopolis had a daughter Chrysorthe, who is thought to have borne a son named Coronus to Apollo. Coronus had two sons, Corax and a younger one Lamedon.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Corax died without issue, and at about this time came Epopeus from <placeName key="tgn,7001399" authname="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName> and took the kingdom. In his reign the first hostile army is said to have invaded the land, which before this had enjoyed unbroken peace. The reason was this. Antiope, the daughter of Nycteus, had a name among the Greeks for beauty, and there was also a report that her father was not Nycteus but Asopus, the river that separates the territories of <placeName key="tgn,7011071" authname="tgn,7011071">Thebes</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7011028" authname="tgn,7011028">Plataea</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>This woman Epopeus carried off but I do not know whether he asked for her hand or adopted a bolder policy from the beginning. The Thebans came against him in arms, and in the battle Nycteus was wounded. Epopeus also was wounded, but won the day. Nycteus they carried back ill to <placeName key="tgn,7011071" authname="tgn,7011071">Thebes</placeName>, and when he was about to die he appointed to be regent of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes" authname="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> his brother Lycus for Labdacus, the son of Polydorus, the son of Cadmus, being still a child, was the ward of Nycteus, who on this occasion entrusted the office of guardian to Lycus. He also besought him to attack Aegialea with a larger army and bring vengeance upon Epopeus; Antiope herself, if taken, was to be punished.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>As to Epopeus, he forthwith offered sacrifice for his victory and began a temple of Athena, and when this was complete he prayed the goddess to make known whether the temple was finished to her liking, and after the prayer they say that olive oil flowed before the temple. Afterwards Epopeus also died of his wound, which he had neglected at first, so that Lycus had now no need to wage war. For Lamedon, the son of Coronus, who became king after Epopeus, gave up Antiope. As she was being taken to <placeName key="perseus,Thebes" authname="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> by way of Eleutherae, she was delivered there on the road.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>On this matter Asius the son of Amphiptolemus<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">fl. <dateRange from="-640" to="-617" authname="-640/-617">640-617 B.C.</dateRange></note> says in his poem:—<quote type="verse"><l met="lyric">Zethus and Amphion had Antiope for their mother,</l><l>Daughter of Asopus, the swift, deep-eddying river,</l><l>Having conceived of Zeus and Epopeus, shepherd of peoples.</l></quote><bibl default="NO">Asius, unknown work</bibl> Homer traces their descent to the more august side of their family, and says that they were the first founders of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes" authname="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, in my opinion distinguishing the lower city from the Cadmea.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>When Lamedon became king he took to wife an Athenian woman, Pheno, the daughter of Clytius. Afterwards also, when war had arisen between him and Archander and Architeles, the sons of Achaeus, he brought in as his ally <placeName key="tgn,7011104" authname="tgn,7011104">Sicyon</placeName> from <placeName key="tgn,7002681" authname="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>, and gave him Zeuxippe his daughter to wife. This man became king, and the land was named after him Sicyonia, and the city <placeName key="tgn,7011104" authname="tgn,7011104">Sicyon</placeName> instead of Aegiale. But they say that <placeName key="tgn,7011104" authname="tgn,7011104">Sicyon</placeName> was not the son of Marathon, the son of Epopeus, but of Metion the son of Erechtheus. Asius confirms their statement, while Hesiod makes <placeName key="tgn,7011104" authname="tgn,7011104">Sicyon</placeName> the son of Erechtheus, and Ibycus says that his father was Pelops.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p><placeName key="tgn,7011104" authname="tgn,7011104">Sicyon</placeName> had a daughter Chthonophyle, and they say that she and Hermes were the parents of Polybus. Afterwards she married Phlias, the son of Dionysus, and gave birth to Androdamas. Polybus gave his daughter Lysianassa to Talaus the son of Bias, king of the Argives; and when Adrastus fled from <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> he came to Polybus at <placeName key="tgn,7011098" authname="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName>, and afterwards on the death of Polybus he became king at <placeName key="tgn,7011098" authname="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName>. When Adrastus returned to <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, Ianiscus, a descendant of Clytius the father-in-law of Lamedon, came from <placeName key="tgn,7002681" authname="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> and was made king, and when Ianiscus died he was succeeded by <placeName key="tgn,7010788" authname="tgn,7010788">Phaestus</placeName>, said to have been one of the children of Heracles.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>After <placeName key="tgn,7010788" authname="tgn,7010788">Phaestus</placeName> in obedience to an oracle migrated to <placeName key="tgn,7012056" authname="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>, the next king is said to have been Zeuxippus, the son of Apollo and the nymph Syllis. On the death of Zeuxippus, Agamemnon led an army against <placeName key="tgn,7011098" authname="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName> and king Hippolytus, the son of Rhopalus, the son of <placeName key="tgn,7010788" authname="tgn,7010788">Phaestus</placeName>. In terror of the army that was attacking him, Hippolytus agreed to become subject to Agamemnon and the Mycenaeans. This Hippolytus was the father of Lacestades. Phalces the son of Temenus, with the Dorians, surprised <placeName key="tgn,7011098" authname="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName> by night, but did Lacestades no harm, because he too was one of the Heracleidae, and made him partner in the kingdom.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />From that time the Sicyonians became Dorians and their land a part of the <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> territory. The city built by Aegialeus on the plain was destroyed by Demetrius the son of Antigonus,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><date value="-303" authname="-303">303 B.C.</date></note> who founded the modern city near what was once the ancient citadel. The reason why the Sicyonians grew weak it would be wrong to seek; we must be content with Homer's saying about Zeus:—<quote type="verse"><l met="dact">Many, indeed, are the cities of which he has levelled the strongholds.</l></quote>When they had lost their power there came upon them an earthquake, which almost depopulated their city and took from them many of their famous sights. It damaged also the cities of <placeName key="tgn,7002358" authname="tgn,7002358">Caria</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7001294" authname="tgn,7001294">Lycia</placeName>, and the island of <placeName key="tgn,7011266" authname="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName> was very violently shaken, so that it was thought that the Sibyl had had her utterance about <placeName key="tgn,7011266" authname="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName><note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">That it should perish and he left destitute.</note> fulfilled.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />When you have come from the Corinthian to the Sicyonian territory you see the tomb of Lycus the Messenian, whoever this Lycus may be; for I can discover no Messenian Lycus who practised the pentathlon<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See p. 157.</note> or won a victory at <placeName key="perseus,Olympia" authname="perseus,Olympia">Olympia</placeName>. This tomb is a mound of earth, but the Sicyonians themselves usually bury their dead in a uniform manner. They cover the body in the ground, and over it they build a basement of stone upon which they set pillars. Above these they put something very like the pediment of a temple. They add no inscription, except that they give the dead man's name without that of his father and bid him farewell.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>After the tomb of Lycus, but on the other side of the Asopus, there is on the right the Olympium, and a little farther on, to the left of the road, the grave of Eupolis,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Flourished at the time of the Peloponnesian war.</note> the Athenian comic poet. Farther on, if you turn in the direction of the city, you see the tomb of Xenodice, who died in childbirth. It has not been made after the native fashion, but so as to harmonize best with the painting, which is very well worth seeing.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Farther on from here is the grave of the Sicyonians who were killed at <placeName key="perseus,Pellene" authname="perseus,Pellene">Pellene</placeName>, at <placeName key="perseus,Dyme" authname="perseus,Dyme">Dyme</placeName> of the Achaeans, in <placeName key="perseus,Megalopolis" authname="perseus,Megalopolis">Megalopolis</placeName> and at <placeName key="perseus,Sellasia" authname="perseus,Sellasia">Sellasia</placeName>.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><date value="-222" authname="-222">222 B.C.</date></note> Their story I will relate more fully presently.  By the gate they have a spring in a cave, the water of which does not rise out of the earth, but flows down from the roof of the cave. For this reason it is called the Dripping Spring.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>On the modern citadel is a sanctuary of Fortune of the Height, and after it one of the Dioscuri. Their images and that of Fortune are of wood. On the stage of the theater built under the citadel is a statue of a man with a shield, who they say is Aratus, the son of Cleinias. After the theater is a temple of Dionysus. The god is of gold and ivory, and by his side are Bacchanals of white marble. These women they say are sacred to Dionysus and maddened by his inspiration. The Sicyonians have also some images which are kept secret. These one night in each year they carry to the temple of Dionysus from what they call the Cosmeterium （Tiring-room）, and they do so with lighted torches and native hymns.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />The first is the one named Baccheus, set up by Androdamas, the son of Phlias, and this is followed by the one called Lysius （Deliverer）, brought from <placeName key="perseus,Thebes" authname="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> by the Theban Phanes at the command of the Pythian priestess. Phanes came to <placeName key="tgn,7011098" authname="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName> when Aristomachus, the son of Cleodaeus, failed to understand the oracle<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">I To wait for “the third fruit,” i.e. the third generation. It was interpreted to mean the third year.</note> given him, and therefore failed to return to the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>. As you walk from the temple of Dionysus to the market-place you see on the right a temple of Artemis of the lake. A look shows that the roof has fallen in, but the inhabitants cannot tell whether the image has been removed or how it was destroyed on the spot.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>Within the market-place is a sanctuary of Persuasion; this too has no image. The worship of Persuasion was established among them for the following reason. When Apollo and Artemis had killed <placeName key="tgn,7010770" authname="tgn,7010770">Pytho</placeName> they came to Aegialea to obtain purification. Dread coming upon them at the place now named Fear, they turned aside to Carmanor in <placeName key="tgn,7012056" authname="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>, and the people of Aegialea were smitten by a plague. When the seers bade them propitiate Apollo and Artemis,</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p>they sent seven boys and seven maidens as suppliants to the river Sythas. They say that the deities, persuaded by these, came to what was then the citadel, and the place that they reached first is the sanctuary of Persuasion. Conformable with this story is the ceremony they perform at the present day; the children go to the Sythas at the feast of Apollo, and having brought, as they pretend, the deities to the sanctuary of Persuasion, they say that they take them back again to the temple of Apollo. The temple stands in the modern market-place, and was originally, it is said, made by Proetus, because in this place his daughters recovered from their madness.</p>
<milestone n="9" unit="section" /><p>It is also said that in this temple Meleager dedicated the spear with which he slew the boar. There is also a story that the flutes of Marsyas are dedicated here. When the Silenus met with his disaster, the river Marsyas carried the flutes to the <placeName key="tgn,1121561" authname="tgn,1121561">Maeander</placeName>; reappearing in the Asopus they were cast ashore in the Sicyonian territory and given to Apollo by the shepherd who found them. I found none of these offerings still in existence, for they were destroyed by fire when the temple was burnt. The temple that I saw, and its image, were dedicated by Pythocles.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />The precinct near the sanctuary of Persuasion that is devoted to Roman emperors was once the house of the tyrant Cleon. He became tyrant in the modern city there was another tyranny while the Sicyonians still lived in the lower city,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">c. <date value="-590" authname="-590">590 B.C.</date></note> that of Cleisthenes, the son of Aristonymus, the son of Myron. Before this house is a hero-shrine of Aratus,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><dateRange from="-271" to="-213" authname="-271/-213">271-213 B.C.</dateRange></note> whose achievements eclipsed those of all contemporary Greeks. His history is as follows.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>After the despotism of Cleon, many of those in authority were seized with such an ungovernable passion for tyranny that two actually became tyrants together, Euthydemus and Timocleidas. These were expelled by the people, who made Cleinias, the father of Aratus, their champion. A few years afterwards Abantidas became tyrant. Before this time Cleinias had met his death, and Aratus went into exile, either of his own accord or because he was compelled to do so by Abantidas. Now Abantidas was killed by some natives, and his father Paseas immediately became tyrant.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>He was killed by Nicocles, who succeeded him.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><date value="-251" authname="-251">251 B.C.</date></note> This Nicocles was attacked by Aratus with a force of Sicyonian exiles and <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> mercenaries. Making his attempt by night, he eluded some of the defenders in the darkness; the others he overcame, and forced his way within the wall. Day was now breaking, and taking the populace with him he hastened to the tyrant's house. This he easily captured, but Nicocles himself succeeded in making his escape. Aratus restored equality of political rights to the Sicyonians, striking a bargain for those in exile; he restored to them their houses and all their other possessions which had been sold, compensating the buyers out of his own purse.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>Moreover, as all the Greeks were afraid of the Macedonians and of Antigonus, the guardian of Philip, the son of Demetrius, he induced the Sicyonians, who were Dorians, to join the Achaean League. He was immediately elected general by the Achaeans, and leading them against the Locrians of <placeName key="perseus,Amphissa" authname="perseus,Amphissa">Amphissa</placeName> and into the land of the Aetolians, their enemies, he ravaged their territory. <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> was held by Antigonus, and there was a Macedonian garrison in the city, but he threw them into a panic by the suddenness of his assault, winning a battle and killing among others Persaeus, the commander of the garrison, who had studied philosophy under Zeno,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The Stoic philosopher （c. <dateRange from="-360" to="-270" authname="-360/-270">360-270 B.C.</dateRange>）.</note> the son of Mnaseas.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>When Aratus had liberated <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, the League was joined by the Epidaurians and Troezenians inhabiting Argolian Acte, and by the Megarians among those beyond the Isthmus, while Ptolemy made an alliance with the Achaeans. The Lacedaemonians and king Agis, the son of Eudamidas, surprised and took <placeName key="perseus,Pellene" authname="perseus,Pellene">Pellene</placeName> by a sudden onslaught, but when Aratus and his army arrived they were defeated in an engagement, evacuated <placeName key="perseus,Pellene" authname="perseus,Pellene">Pellene</placeName>, and returned home under a truce.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>After his success in the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>, Aratus thought it a shame to allow the Macedonians to hold unchallenged Peiraeus, Munychia, <placeName key="tgn,7002340" authname="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName>, and Sunium; but not expecting to be able to take them by force he bribed Diogenes, the commander of the garrisons, to give up the positions for a hundred and fifty talents, himself helping the Athenians by contributing a sixth part of the sum. He induced Aristomachus also, the tyrant of <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, to restore to the Argives their democracy and to join the Achaean League; he captured <placeName key="perseus,Mantinea" authname="perseus,Mantinea">Mantinea</placeName> from the Lacedaemonians who held it. But no man finds all his plans turn out according to his liking, and even Aratus was compelled to become an ally of the Macedonians and Antigonus in the following way.</p>
<milestone n="9" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Cleomenes, the son of Leonidas, the son of Cleonymus, having succeeded to the kingship at <placeName key="perseus,Sparta" authname="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, resembled Pausanias<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The victor of <placeName key="perseus,Plataea" authname="perseus,Plataea">Plataea</placeName> （<date value="-479" authname="-479">479 B.C.</date>）. Afterwards put to death for treachery.</note> in being dissatisfied with the established constitution and in aiming at a tyranny. A more fiery man than Pausanias, and no coward, he quickly succeeded by spirit and daring in accomplishing all his ambition. He poisoned Eurydamidas, the king of the other<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">There were two kings at <placeName key="perseus,Sparta" authname="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, one from each of the two royal houses.</note> royal house, while yet a boy, raised to the throne by means of the ephors his brother Epicleidas, destroyed the power of the senate, and appointed in its stead a nominal Council of Fathers. Ambitious for greater things and for supremacy over the Greeks, he first attacked the Achaeans, hoping if successful to have them as allies, and especially wishing that they should not hinder his activities.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>Engaging them at <placeName key="perseus,Dyme" authname="perseus,Dyme">Dyme</placeName> beyond <placeName key="tgn,7011025" authname="tgn,7011025">Patrae</placeName>, Aratus being still leader of the Achaeans, he won the victory.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><date value="-225" authname="-225">225 B.C.</date></note> In fear for the Achaeans and for <placeName key="tgn,7011098" authname="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName> itself, Aratus was forced by this defeat to bring in Antigouus as an ally. Cleomenes had violated the peace which he had made with Antigonus and had openly acted in many ways contrary to treaty, especially in laying waste <placeName key="perseus,Megalopolis" authname="perseus,Megalopolis">Megalopolis</placeName>. So Antigonus crossed into the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName> and the Achaeans met Cleomenes at <placeName key="perseus,Sellasia" authname="perseus,Sellasia">Sellasia</placeName>.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><date value="-222" authname="-222">222 B.C.</date></note> The Achaeans were victorious, the people of <placeName key="perseus,Sellasia" authname="perseus,Sellasia">Sellasia</placeName> were sold into slavery, and <placeName key="tgn,7011065" authname="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName> itself was captured. Antigonus and the Achaeans restored to the Lacedaemonians the constitution of their fathers;</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>but of the children of Leonidas, Epicleidas was killed in the battle, and Cleomenes fled to <placeName key="tgn,7016833" authname="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>. Held in the highest honor by Ptolemy, he came to be cast into prison, being convicted of inciting Egyptians to rebel against their king. He made his escape from prison and began a riot among the Alexandrians, but at last, on being captured, he fell by his own hand. The Lacedaemonians, glad to be rid of Cleomenes, refused to be ruled by kings any longer, but the rest of their ancient constitution they have kept to the present day. Antigonus remained a constant friend of Aratus, looking upon him as a benefactor who hid helped him to accomplish brilliant deeds.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>But when Philip succeeded to the throne, since Aratus did not approve of his violent treatment of his subjects, and in some cases even opposed the accomplishment of his purposes, he killed Aratus by giving him secretly a dose of poison. This fate came upon Aratus at Aegium, from which place he was carried to <placeName key="tgn,7011098" authname="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName> and buried, and there is still in that city the hero-shrine of Aratus. Philip treated two Athenians, Eurycleides and Micon, in a similar way. These men also, who were orators enjoying the confidence of the people, he killed by poison.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>After all, Philip himself in his turn was fated to suffer disaster through the fatal cup. Philip's son, Demetrius, was poisoned by Perseus, his younger son, and grief at the murder brought the father also to his grave. I mention the incident in passing, with my mind turned to the inspired words of the poet Hesiod,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hes. WD 265" default="NO" valid="yes">Hes. WD 265</bibl></note> that he who plots mischief against his neighbor directs it first to himself.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />After the hero-shrine of Aratus is an altar to Isthmian Poseidon, and also a Zeus Meilichius （Gracious） and an Artemis named Patroa （Paternal）, both of them very inartistic works. The Meilichius is like a pyramid, the Artemis like a pillar. Here too stand their council-chamber and a portico called Cleisthenean from the name of him who built it. It was built from spoils by Cleisthenes, who helped the Amphictyons in the war at <placeName key="tgn,6001466" authname="tgn,6001466">Cirrha</placeName>.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">c. <date value="-590" authname="-590">590 B.C.</date></note> In the market-place under the open sky is a bronze Zeus, a work of Lysippus,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Contemporary of Alexander the Great.</note> and by the side of it a gilded Artemis.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>Hard by is a sanctuary of Apollo Lycius （Wolf-god）, now fallen into ruins and not worth any attention. For wolves once so preyed upon their flocks that there was no longer any profit therefrom, and the god, mentioning a certain place where lay a dry log, gave an oracle that the bark of this log mixed with meat was to be set out for the beasts to eat. As soon as they tasted it the bark killed them, and that log lay in my time in the sanctuary of the Wolf-god, but not even the guides of the Sicyonians knew what kind of tree it was.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p>Next after this are bronze portrait statues, said to be the daughters of Proetus, but the inscription I found referred to other women. Here there is a bronze Heracles, made by Lysippus the Sicyonian, and hard by stands Hermes of the Market-place.</p>
<milestone n="10" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />In the gymnasium not far from the market-place is dedicated a stone Heracles made by Scopas.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Flourished first half of fourth century B.C.</note> There is also in another place a sanctuary of Heracles. The whole of the enclosure here they name Paedize; in the middle of the enclosure is the sanctuary, and in it is an old wooden figure carved by Laphaes the Phliasian. I will now describe the ritual at the festival. The story is that on coming to the Sicyonian land <placeName key="tgn,7010788" authname="tgn,7010788">Phaestus</placeName> found the people giving offerings to Heracles as to a hero. <placeName key="tgn,7010788" authname="tgn,7010788">Phaestus</placeName> then refused to do anything of the kind, but insisted on sacrificing to him as to a god. Even at the present day the Sicyonians, after slaying a lamb and burning the thighs upon the altar, eat some of the meat as part of a victim given to a god, while the rest they offer as to a hero. The first day of the festival in honor of Heracles they name . . . ; the second they call <placeName key="tgn,7008299" authname="tgn,7008299">Heraclea</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>From here is a way to a sanctuary of Asclepius. On passing into the enclosure you see on the left a building with two rooms. In the outer room lies a figure of Sleep, of which nothing remains now except the head. The inner room is given over to the Carnean Apollo; into it none may enter except the priests. In the portico lies a huge bone of a sea-monster, and after it an image of the Dream-god and Sleep, surnamed Epidotes （Bountiful）, lulling to sleep a lion. Within the sanctuary on either side of the entrance is an image, on the one hand Pan seated, on the other Artemis standing.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />When you have entered you see the god, a beardless figure of gold and ivory made by Calamis.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">A famous early fifth century sculptor.</note> He holds a staff in one hand, and a cone of the cultivated pine in the other. The Sicyonians say that the god was carried to them from <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName> on a carriage drawn by two mules, that he was in the likeness of a serpent, and that he was brought by Nicagora of <placeName key="tgn,7011098" authname="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName>, the mother of Agasicles and the wife of Echetimus. Here are small figures hanging from the roof. She who is on the serpent they say is Aristodama, the mother of Aratus, whom they hold to be a son of Asclepius.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>Such are the noteworthy things that this enclosure presented to me, and opposite is another enclosure, sacred to Aphrodite. The first thing inside is a statue of Antiope. They say that her sons were Sicyonians, and because of them the Sicyonians will have it that Antiope herself is related to themselves. After this is the sanctuary of Aphrodite, into which enter only a female verger, who after her appointment may not have intercourse with a man, and a virgin, called the Bath-bearer, holding her sacred office for a year. All others are wont to behold the goddess from the entrance, and to pray from that place.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>The image, which is seated, was made by the Sicyonian Canachus, who also fashioned the Apollo at <placeName key="perseus,Didyma" authname="perseus,Didyma">Didyma</placeName> of the Milesians, and the Ismenian Apollo for the Thebans. It is made of gold and ivory, having on its head a polos,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">A curiously shaped head-gear.</note> and carrying in one hand a poppy and in the other an apple. They offer the thighs of the victims, excepting pigs; the other parts they burn for the goddess with juniper wood, but as the thighs are burning they add to the offering a leaf of the paideros.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />This is a plant in the open parts of the enclosure, and it grows nowhere else either in Sicyonia or in any other land. Its leaves are smaller than those of the esculent oak, but larger than those of the holm; the shape is similar to that of the oak-leaf. One side is of a dark color, the other is white. You might best compare the color to that of white-poplar leaves.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Ascending from here to the gymnasium you see in the right a sanctuary of Artemis Pheraea. It is said that the wooden image was brought from Pherae. This gymnasium was built for the Sicyonians by Cleinias, and they still train the youths here. White marble images are here, an Artemis wrought only to the waist, and a Heracles whose lower parts are similar to the square Hermae.</p>
<milestone n="11" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Turning away from here towards the gate called Holy you see, not far from the gate, a temple of Athena. Dedicated long ago by Epopeus, it surpassed all its contemporaries in size and splendor. Yet the memory of even this was doomed to perish through lapse of time—it was burnt down by lightning—but the altar there, which escaped injury, remains down to the present day as Epopeus made it. Before the altar a barrow has been raised for Epopeus himself, and near the grave are the gods Averters of evil. Near them the Greeks perform such rites as they are wont to do in order to avert misfortunes. They say that the neighboring sanctuary of Artemis and Apollo was also made by Epopeus, and that of Hera after it by Adrastus. I found no images remaining in either. Behind the sanctuary of Hera he built an altar to Pan, and one to Helius （Sun） made of white marble.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>On the way down to the plain is a sanctuary of Demeter, said to have been founded by Plemnaeis as a thank-offering to the goddess for the rearing of his son. A little farther away from the sanctuary of Hera founded by Adrastus is a temple of the Carnean Apollo. Only the pillars are standing in it; you will no longer find there walls or roof, nor yet in that of Hera Pioneer. This temple was founded by Phalces, son of Temenus, who asserted that Hera guided him on the road to <placeName key="tgn,7011098" authname="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>On the direct road from <placeName key="tgn,7011098" authname="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName> to Phlius, on the left of the road and just about ten stades from it, is a grove called Pyraea, and in it a sanctuary of Hera Protectress and the Maid. Here the men celebrate a festival by themselves, giving up to the women the temple called Nymphon for the purposes of their festival. In the Nymphon are images of Dionysus, Demeter, and the Maid, with only their faces exposed. The road to <placeName key="perseus,Titane" authname="perseus,Titane">Titane</placeName> is sixty stades long, and too narrow to be used by carriages drawn by a yoke.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>At a distance along it, in my opinion, of twenty stades, to the left on the other side of the Asopus, is a grove of holm oaks and a temple of the goddesses named by the Athenians the August, and by the Sicyonians the Kindly Ones. On one day in each year they celebrate a festival to them and offer sheep big with young as a burnt offering, and they are accustomed to use a libation of honey and water, and flowers instead of garlands. They practise similar rites at the altar of the Fates; it is in an open space in the grove.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>On turning back to the road, and having crossed the Asopus again and reached the summit of the hill, you come to the place where the natives say that Titan first dwelt. They add that he was the brother of Helius （Sun）, and that after him the place got the name <placeName key="perseus,Titane" authname="perseus,Titane">Titane</placeName>. My own view is that he proved clever at observing the seasons of the year and the times when the sun increases and ripens seeds and fruits, and for this reason was held to be the brother of Helius. Afterwards Alexanor, the son of Machaon, the son of Asclepius, came to Sicyonia and built the sanctuary of Asclepius at <placeName key="perseus,Titane" authname="perseus,Titane">Titane</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>The neighbors are chiefly servants of the god, and within the enclosure are old cypress trees. One cannot learn of what wood or metal the image is, nor do they know the name of the maker, though one or two attribute it to Alexanor himself. Of the image can be seen only the face, hands, and feet, for it has about it a tunic of white wool and a cloak. There is a similar image of Health; this, too, one cannot see easily because it is so surrounded with the locks of women, who cut them off and offer them to the goddess, and with strips of Babylonian raiment. With whichever of these a votary here is willing to propitiate heaven, the same instructions have been given to him, to worship this image which they are pleased to call Health.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>There are images also of Alexanor and of Euamerion; to the former they give offerings as to a hero after the setting of the sun; to Euamerion, as being a god, they give burnt sacrifices. If I conjecture aright, the Pergamenes, in accordance with an oracle, call this Euamerion Telesphorus （Accomplisher） while the Epidaurians call him Acesis （Cure）. There is also a wooden image of Coronis, but it has no fixed position anywhere in the temple. While to the god are being sacrificed a bull, a lamb, and a pig, they remove Coronis to the sanctuary of Athena and honor her there. The parts of the victims which they offer as a burnt sacrifice, and they are not content with cutting out the thighs, they burn on the ground, except the birds, which they burn on the altar.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />In the gable at the ends are figures of Heracles and of Victories. In the portico are dedicated images of Dionysus and Hecate, with Aphrodite, the Mother of the gods, and Fortune. These are wooden, but Asclepius, surnamed Gortynian, is of stone. They are unwilling to enter among the sacred serpents through fear, but they place their food before the entrance and take no further trouble. Within the enclosure is a bronze statue of a Sicyonian named Granianus, who won the following victories at <placeName key="perseus,Olympia" authname="perseus,Olympia">Olympia</placeName>: the pentathlon<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See note on <bibl n="Paus. 1.29.5" default="NO" valid="yes">Paus. 1.29.5</bibl></note> twice, the foot-race, the double-course foot-race twice, once without and once with the shield.</p>
<milestone n="12" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />In <placeName key="perseus,Titane" authname="perseus,Titane">Titane</placeName> there is also a sanctuary of Athena, into which they bring up the image of Coronis. In it is an old wooden figure of Athena, and I was told that it, too, was struck by lightning. The sanctuary is built upon a hill, at the bottom of which is an Altar of the Winds, and on it the priest sacrifices to the winds one night in every year. He also performs other secret rites at four pits, taming the fierceness of the blasts, and he is said to chant as well charms of Medea.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />On reaching <placeName key="tgn,7011098" authname="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName> from <placeName key="perseus,Titane" authname="perseus,Titane">Titane</placeName>, as you go down to the shore you see on the left of the road a temple of Hera having now neither image nor roof. They say that its founder was Proetus, the son of Abas. When you have gone down to the harbor called the Sicyonians' and turned towards Aristonautae, the Port of <placeName key="perseus,Pellene" authname="perseus,Pellene">Pellene</placeName>, you see a little above the road on the left hand a sanctuary of Poseidon. Farther along the highway is a river called the Helisson, and after it the Sythas, both emptying themselves into the sea.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>Phliasia borders on Sicyonia. The city is just about forty stades distant from <placeName key="perseus,Titane" authname="perseus,Titane">Titane</placeName>, and there is a straight road to it from <placeName key="tgn,7011098" authname="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName>. That the Phliasians are in no way related to the Arcadians is shown by the passage in Homer that deals with the list of the Arcadians, in which the Sicyonians are not included among the Arcadian confederates. As my narrative progresses it will become clear that they were <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> originally, and became Dorian later after the return of the Heracleidae to the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>. I know that most of the traditions concerning the Phliasians are contradictory, but I shall make use of those which have been most generally accepted.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>They say that the first man in this land was <placeName key="tgn,7002838" authname="tgn,7002838">Aras</placeName>, who sprang from the soil. He founded a city around that hillock which even down to our day is called the Arantine Hill, not far distant from a second hill on which the Phliasians have their citadel and their sanctuary of Hebe. Here, then, he founded a city, and after him in ancient times both the land and the city were called Arantia. While he was king, Asopus, said to be the son of Celusa and Poseidon, discovered for him the water of the river which the present inhabitants call after him Asopus. The tomb of Aras is in the place called Celeae, where they say is also buried Dysaules of <placeName key="perseus,Eleusis" authname="perseus,Eleusis">Eleusis</placeName>.</p>
    <milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" /><placeName key="tgn,7002838" authname="tgn,7002838">Aras</placeName> had a son Aoris and a daughter Araethyrea, who, the Phliasians say, were experienced hunters and brave warriors. Araethyrea died first, and Aoris, in memory of his sister, changed the name of the land to Araethyrea. This is why Homer, in making a list of Agamemnon's subjects, has the verse:<quote type="verse"><l met="dact">Orneae was their home and Araethyrea the delightful.</l></quote><bibl n="Hom. Il. 2.571" default="NO" valid="yes">Hom. Il. 2.571</bibl>The graves of the children of <placeName key="tgn,7002838" authname="tgn,7002838">Aras</placeName> are, in my opinion, on the Arantine Hill and not in any other part of the land. On the top of them are far-seen gravestones, and before the celebration of the mysteries of Demeter the people look at these tombs and call <placeName key="tgn,7002838" authname="tgn,7002838">Aras</placeName> and his children to the libations.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>The Argives say that Phlias, who has given the land its third name, was the son of Ceisus, the son of Temenus. This account I can by no means accept, but I know that he is called a son of Dionysus, and that he is said to have been one of those who sailed on the <placeName key="tgn,1094163" authname="tgn,1094163">Argo</placeName>. The verses of the Rhodian poet confirm me in my opinion:—<quote type="verse"><l met="dact">Came after these Phlias from Araethyrea to the muster;</l><l>Here did he dwell and prosper, because Dionysus his father</l><l>Cared for him well, and his home was near to the springs of Asopus.</l></quote><bibl n="Apollon. 1.115" default="NO" valid="yes">Apollonius Rhodius Argonautica 1.115-117.</bibl>The account goes on to say that the mother of Phlias was Araethyrea and not Chthonophyle. The latter was his wife and bore him Androdamas.</p>
<milestone n="13" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />On the return of the Heracleidae disturbances took place throughout the whole of the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName> except <placeName key="tgn,7002735" authname="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName>, so that many of the cities received additional settlers from the Dorian race, and their inhabitants suffered yet more revolutions. The history of Phlius is as follows. The Dorian Rhegnidas, the son of Phalces, the son of Temenus, attacked it from <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> and Sicyonia. Some of the Phliasians were inclined to accept the offer of Rhegnidas, which was that they should remain on their own estates and receive Rhegnidas as their king, giving the Dorians with him a share in the land.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>Hippasus and his party, on the other hand, urged the citizens to defend themselves, and not to give up many advantages to the Dorians without striking a blow. The people, however, accepted the opposite policy, and so Hippasus and any others who wished fled to <placeName key="tgn,7002673" authname="tgn,7002673">Samos</placeName>. Great-grandson of this Hippasus was Pythagoras,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The philosopher and mathematician.Fl. c. <date value="-527" authname="-527">527 B.C.</date></note> the celebrated sage. For Pythagoras was the son of Mnesarchus, the son of Euphranor, the son of Hippasus. This is the account the Phliasians give about themselves, and the Sicyonians in general agree with them.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>I will now add an account of the most remarkable of their famous sights. On the Phliasian citadel is a grove of cypress trees and a sanctuary which from ancient times has been held to be peculiarly holy. The earliest Phliasians named the goddess to whom the sanctuary belongs Ganymeda; but later authorities call her Hebe, whom Homer<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 4.2" default="NO" valid="yes">Hom. Il. 4.2</bibl> foll.</note> mentions in the duel between Menelaus and Alexander, saying that she was the cup-bearer of the gods; and again he says, in the descent of Odysseus to Hell,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Od. 11.603" default="NO" valid="yes">Hom. Od. 11.603</bibl></note> that she was the wife of Heracles. <placeName key="tgn,1115310" authname="tgn,1115310">Olen</placeName>,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">A mythical poet of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, associated with Apollo.</note> in his hymn to Hera, says that Hera was reared by the Seasons, and that her children were Ares and Hebe. Of the honors that the Phliasians pay to this goddess the greatest is the pardoning of suppliants.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>All those who seek sanctuary here receive full forgiveness, and prisoners, when set free, dedicate their fetters on the trees in the grove. The Phliasians also celebrate a yearly festival which they call Ivy-cutters. There is no image, either kept in secret or openly displayed, and the reason for this is set forth in a sacred legend of theirs though on the left as you go out is a temple of Hera with an image of Parian marble.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />On the citadel is another enclosure, which is sacred to Demeter, and in it are a temple and statue of Demeter and her daughter. Here there is also a bronze statue of Artemis, which appeared to me to be ancient. As you go down from the citadel you see on the right a temple of Asclepius with an image of the god as a beardless youth. Below this temple is built a theater. Not far from it is a sanctuary of Demeter and old, seated images.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>On the market-place is a votive offering, a bronze she-goat for the most part covered with gold. The following is the reason why it has received honors among the Phliasians. The constellation which they call the Goat on its rising causes continual damage to the vines. In order that they may suffer nothing unpleasant from it, the Phliasians pay honors to the bronze goat on the market-place and adorn the image with gold. Here also is the tomb of Aristias, the son of Pratinas.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">fl. c. <date value="-500" authname="-500">500 B.C.</date></note> This Aristias and his father Pratinas composed satyric plays more popular than any save those of Aeschylus.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>Behind the market-place is a building which the Phliasians name the House of Divination. Into it Amphiaraus entered, slept the night there, and then first, say the Phliasians, began to divine. According to their account Amphiaraus was for a time an ordinary person and no diviner. Ever since that time the building has been shut up. Not far away is what is called the Omphalos （Navel）, the center of all the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>, if they speak the truth about it. Farther on from the Omphalos they have an old sanctuary of Dionysus, a sanctuary of Apollo, and one of Isis. The image of Dionysus is visible to all, and so also is that of Apollo, but the image of Isis only the priests may behold.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />The Phliasians tell also the following legend. When Heracles came back safe from <placeName key="tgn,1000172" authname="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName>, bringing the apples of the Hesperides, as they were called, he visited Phlius on some private matter. While he was staying there Oeneus came to him from <placeName key="tgn,7002678" authname="tgn,7002678">Aetolia</placeName>. He had already allied himself to the family of Heracles, and after his arrival on this occasion either he entertained Heracles or Heracles entertained him. Be this as it may, displeased with the drink given him Heracles struck on the head with one of his fingers the boy Cyathus, the cup-bearer of Oeneus, who died on the spot from the blow. A chapel keeps the memory of the deed fresh among the Phliasians; it is built by the side of the sanctuary of Apollo, and it contains statues made of stone representing Cyathus holding out a cup to Heracles.</p>
<milestone n="14" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Celeae is some five stades distant from the city, and here they celebrate the mysteries in honor of Demeter, not every year but every fourth year. The initiating priest is not appointed for life, but at each celebration they elect a fresh one, who takes, if he cares to do so, a wife. In this respect their custom differs from that at <placeName key="perseus,Eleusis" authname="perseus,Eleusis">Eleusis</placeName>, but the actual celebration is modelled on the Eleusinian rites. The Phliasians themselves admit that they copy the “performance” at <placeName key="perseus,Eleusis" authname="perseus,Eleusis">Eleusis</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>They say that it was Dysaules, the brother of Celeus, who came to their land and established the mysteries, and that he had been expelled from <placeName key="perseus,Eleusis" authname="perseus,Eleusis">Eleusis</placeName> by Ion, when Ion, the son of Xuthus, was chosen by the Athenians to be commander-in-chief in the Eleusinian war. Now I cannot possibly agree with the Phliasians in supposing that an Eleusinian was conquered in battle and driven away into exile, for the war terminated in a treaty before it was fought out, and Eumolpus himself remained at <placeName key="perseus,Eleusis" authname="perseus,Eleusis">Eleusis</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>But it is possible that Dysaules came to Phlius for some other reason than that given by the Phliasians. I do not believe either that he was related to Celeus, or that he was in any way distinguished at <placeName key="perseus,Eleusis" authname="perseus,Eleusis">Eleusis</placeName>, otherwise Homer would never have passed him by in his poems. For Homer is one of those who have written in honor of Demeter, and when he is making a list of those to whom the goddess taught the mysteries he knows nothing of an Eleusinian named Dysaules. These are the verses:—<quote type="verse"><l met="dact">She to Triptolemus taught, and to Diocles, driver of horses,</l><l>Also to mighty Eumolpus, to Celeus, leader of peoples,</l><l>Cult of the holy rites, to them all her mystery telling.</l></quote><bibl n="HH 2.474" default="NO" valid="yes">HH Dem. 474-476</bibl></p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>At all events, this Dysaules, according to the Phliasians, established the mysteries here, and he it was who gave to the place the name Celeae. I have already said that the tomb of Dysaules is here. So the grave of <placeName key="tgn,7002838" authname="tgn,7002838">Aras</placeName> was made earlier, for according to the account of the Phliasians Dysaules did not arrive in the reign of <placeName key="tgn,7002838" authname="tgn,7002838">Aras</placeName>, but later. For <placeName key="tgn,7002838" authname="tgn,7002838">Aras</placeName>, they say, was a contemporary of Prometheus, the son of Iapetus, and three generations of men older than Pelasgus the son of Arcas and those called at <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> aboriginals. On the roof of what is called the Anactorum they say is dedicated the chariot of Pelops.</p>
<milestone n="15" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />These are the things that I found most worthy of mention among the Phliasians. On the road from <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> to <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> is a small city Cleonae. They say that Cleones was a son of Pelops, though there are some who say that Cleone was one of the daughters of Asopus, that flows by the side of <placeName key="tgn,7011104" authname="tgn,7011104">Sicyon</placeName>. Be this as it may, one or other of these two accounts for the name of the city. Here there is a sanctuary of Athena, and the image is a work of Scyllis and Dipoenus.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">fl. sixth cent. B.C.</note> Some hold them to have been the pupils of Daedalus, but others will have it that Daedalus took a wife from <placeName key="perseus,Gortyn" authname="perseus,Gortyn">Gortyn</placeName>, and that Dipoenus and Scyllis were his sons by this woman. Cleonae possesses this sanctuary and the tomb of Eurytus and Cteatus. The story is that as they were going as ambassadors from <placeName key="perseus,Elis" authname="perseus,Elis">Elis</placeName> to the Isthmian contest they were here shot by Heracles, who charged them with being his adversaries in the war against Augeas.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>From Cleonae to <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> are two roads; one is direct and only for active men, the other goes along the pass called Tretus （Pierced）, is narrow like the other, being surrounded by mountains, but is nevertheless more suitable for carriages. In these mountains is still shown the cave of the famous lion, and the place <placeName key="perseus,Nemea" authname="perseus,Nemea">Nemea</placeName> is distant some fifteen stades. In <placeName key="perseus,Nemea" authname="perseus,Nemea">Nemea</placeName> is a noteworthy temple of Nemean Zeus, but I found that the roof had fallen in and that there was no longer remaining any image. Around the temple is a grove of cypress trees, and here it is, they say, that Opheltes was placed by his nurse in the grass and killed by the serpent.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>The Argives offer burnt sacrifices to Zeus in <placeName key="perseus,Nemea" authname="perseus,Nemea">Nemea</placeName> also, and elect a priest of Nemean Zeus; moreover they offer a prize for a race in armour at the winter celebration of the Nemean games. In this place is the grave of Opheltes; around it is a fence of stones, and within the enclosure are altars. There is also a mound of earth which is the tomb of Lycurgus, the father of Opheltes. The spring they call Adrastea for some reason or other, perhaps because Adrastus found it. The land was named, they say, after <placeName key="perseus,Nemea" authname="perseus,Nemea">Nemea</placeName>, who was another daughter of Asopus. Above Nemea is Mount Apesas, where they say that Perseus first sacrificed to Zeus of Apesas.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>Ascending to Tretus, and again going along the road to <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, you see on the left the ruins of <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName>. The Greeks are aware that the founder of <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName> was Perseus, so I will narrate the cause of its foundation and the reason why the Argives afterwards laid <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName> waste. The oldest tradition in the region now called <placeName key="tgn,7002739" authname="tgn,7002739">Argolis</placeName> is that when Inachus was king he named the river after himself and sacrificed to Hera.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />There is also another legend which says that Phoroneus was the first inhabitant of this land, and that Inachus, the father of Phoroneus, was not a man but the river. This river, with the rivers Cephisus and Asterion, judged concerning the land between Poseidon and Hera. They decided that the land belonged to Hera, and so Poseidon made their waters disappear. For this reason neither Inachus nor either of the other rivers I have mentioned provides any water except after rain. In summer their streams are dry except those at <placeName key="perseus,Lerna" authname="perseus,Lerna">Lerna</placeName>. Phoroneus, the son of Inachus, was the first to gather together the inhabitants, who up to that time had been scattered and living as isolated families. The place into which they were first gathered was named the City of Phoroneus.</p>
<milestone n="16" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Argus, the grandson of Phoroneus, succeeding to the throne after Phoroneus, gave his name to the land. Argus begat Peirasus and Phorbas, Phorbas begat Triopas, and Triopas begat Iasus and Agenor. Io, the daughter of Iasus, went to <placeName key="tgn,7016833" authname="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, whether the circumstances be as Herodotus records or as the Greeks say. After Iasus, Crotopus, the son of Agenor, came to the throne and begat Sthenelas, but Danaus sailed from <placeName key="tgn,7016833" authname="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> against Gelanor, the son of Sthenelas, and stayed the succession to the kingdom of the descendants of Agenor. What followed is known to all alike: the crime the daughters of Danaus committed against their cousins, and how, on the death of Danaus, Lynceus succeeded him.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>But the sons of Abas, the son of Lynceus, divided the kingdom between themselves; Acrisius remained where he was at <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, and Proetus took over the Heraeum, Mideia, <placeName key="perseus,Tiryns" authname="perseus,Tiryns">Tiryns</placeName>, and the <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> coast region. Traces of the residence of Proetus in <placeName key="perseus,Tiryns" authname="perseus,Tiryns">Tiryns</placeName> remain to the present day. Afterwards Acrisius, learning that Perseus himself was not only alive but accomplishing great achievements, retired to <placeName key="tgn,7010894" authname="tgn,7010894">Larisa</placeName> on the Peneus. And Perseus, wishing at all costs to see the father of his mother and to greet him with fair words and deeds, visited him at <placeName key="tgn,7010894" authname="tgn,7010894">Larisa</placeName>. Being in the prime of life and proud of his inventing the quoit, he gave displays before all, and Acrisius, as luck would have it, stepped unnoticed into the path of the quoit.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>So the prediction of the god to Acrisius found its fulfillment, nor was his fate prevented by his precautions against his daughter and grandson. Perseus, ashamed because of the gossip about the homicide, on his return to <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> induced Megapenthes, the son of Proetus, to make an exchange of kingdoms; taking over himself that of Megapenthes, he founded <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName>. For on its site the cap （myces） fell from his scabbard, and he regarded this as a sign to found a city. I have also heard the following account. He was thirsty, and the thought occurred to him to pick up a mushroom （myces） from the ground. Drinking with joy water that flowed from it, he gave to the place the name of <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>Homer in the <title>Odyssey</title> mentions a woman Mycene in the following verse:—<quote type="verse"><l met="dact">Tyro and Alcmene and the fair-crowned lady Mycene.</l></quote><bibl default="NO">Hom. Od., unknown line</bibl>. She is said to have been the daughter of Inachus and the wife of Arestor in the poem which the Greeks call the <title>Great Eoeae</title>. So they say that this lady has given her name to the city. But the account which is attributed to Acusilaus, that Myceneus was the son of Sparton, and Sparton of Phoroneus, I cannot accept, because the Lacedaemonians themselves do not accept it either. For the Lacedaemonians have at Amyclae a portrait statue of a woman named Sparte, but they would be amazed at the mere mention of a Sparton, son of Phoroneus.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>It was jealousy which caused the Argives to destroy <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName>. For at the time of the Persian invasion the Argives made no move, but the Mycenaeans sent eighty men to Thermopylae who shared in the achievement of the Lacedaemonians. This eagerness for distinction brought ruin upon them by exasperating the Argives. There still remain, however, parts of the city wall, including the gate, upon which stand lions. These, too, are said to be the work of the Cyclopes, who made for Proetus the wall at <placeName key="perseus,Tiryns" authname="perseus,Tiryns">Tiryns</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>In the ruins of <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName> is a fountain called Persea; there are also underground chambers of Atreus and his children, in which were stored their treasures. There is the grave of Atreus, along with the graves of such as returned with Agamemnon from <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, and were murdered by Aegisthus after he had given them a banquet. As for the tomb of Cassandra, it is claimed by the Lacedaemonians who dwell around Amyclae. Agamemnon has his tomb, and so has Eurymedon the charioteer, while another is shared by Teledamus and Pelops, twin sons, they say, of Cassandra,</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />whom while yet babies Aegisthus slew after their parents. Electra has her tomb, for Orestes married her to Pylades. Hellanicus adds that the children of Pylades by Electra were Medon and Strophius. Clytemnestra and Aegisthus were buried at some little distance from the wall. They were thought unworthy of a place within it, where lay Agamemnon himself and those who were murdered with him.</p>
<milestone n="17" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Fifteen stades distant from <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName> is on the left the Heraeum. Beside the road flows the brook called Water of Freedom. The priestesses use it in purifications and for such sacrifices as are secret. The sanctuary itself is on a lower part of <placeName key="tgn,7002677" authname="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>. <placeName key="tgn,7002677" authname="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName> is the name they give to the hill here, saying that Asterion the river had three daughters, <placeName key="tgn,7002677" authname="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Prosymna" authname="perseus,Prosymna">Prosymna</placeName>, and Acraea, and that they were nurses of Hera.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>The hill opposite the Heraeum they name after Acraea, the environs of the sanctuary they name after <placeName key="tgn,7002677" authname="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>, and the land beneath the Heraeum after <placeName key="perseus,Prosymna" authname="perseus,Prosymna">Prosymna</placeName>. This Asterion flows above the Heraeum, and falling into a cleft disappears. On its banks grows a plant, which also is called asterion. They offer the plant itself to Hera, and from its leaves weave her garlands.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>It is said that the architect of the temple was Eupolemus, an <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName>. The sculptures carved above the pillars refer either to the birth of Zeus and the battle between the gods and the giants, or to the Trojan war and the capture of <placeName key="tgn,7002329" authname="tgn,7002329">Ilium</placeName>. Before the entrance stand statues of women who have been priestesses to Hera and of various heroes, including Orestes. They say that Orestes is the one with the inscription, that it represents the Emperor Augustus. In the fore-temple are on the one side ancient statues of the Graces, and on the right a couch of Hera and a votive offering, the shield which Menelaus once took from Euphorbus at <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>The statue of Hera is seated on a throne; it is huge, made of gold and ivory, and is a work of Polycleitus. She is wearing a crown with Graces and Seasons worked upon it, and in one hand she carries a pomegranate and in the other a sceptre. About the pomegranate I must say nothing, for its story is somewhat of a holy mystery. The presence of a cuckoo seated on the sceptre they explain by the story that when Zeus was in love with Hera in her maidenhood he changed himself into this bird, and she caught it to be her pet. This tale and similar legends about the gods I relate without believing them, but I relate them nevertheless.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>By the side of Hera stands what is said to be an image of Hebe fashioned by Naucydes; it, too, is of ivory and gold. By its side is an old image of Hera on a pillar. The oldest image is made of wild-pear wood, and was dedicated in <placeName key="perseus,Tiryns" authname="perseus,Tiryns">Tiryns</placeName> by Peirasus, son of Argus, and when the Argives destroyed <placeName key="perseus,Tiryns" authname="perseus,Tiryns">Tiryns</placeName> they carried it away to the Heraeum. I myself saw it, a small, seated image.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>Of the votive offerings the following are noteworthy. There is an altar upon which is wrought in relief the fabled marriage of Hebe and Heracles. This is of silver, but the peacock dedicated by the Emperor Hadrian is of gold and gleaming stones. He dedicated it because they hold the bird to be sacred to Hera. There lie here a golden crown and a purple robe, offerings of Nero.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>Above this temple are the foundations of the earlier temple and such parts of it as were spared by the flames. It was burnt down because sleep overpowered Chryseis, the priestess of Hera, when the lamp before the wreaths set fire to them. Chryseis went to <placeName key="perseus,Tegea" authname="perseus,Tegea">Tegea</placeName> and supplicated Athena Alea. Although so great a disaster had befallen them the Argives did not take down the statue of Chryseis; it is still in position in front of the burnt temple.</p>
<milestone n="18" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />By the side of the road from <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae" authname="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName> to <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> there is on the left hand a hero-shrine of Perseus. The neighboring folk, then, pay him honors here, but the greatest honors are paid to him in Seriphus and among the Athenians, who have a precinct sacred to Perseus and an altar of Dictys and Clymene, who are called the saviours of Perseus. Advancing a little way in the <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> territory from this hero-shrine one sees on the right the grave of Thyestes. On it is a stone ram, because Thyestes obtained the golden lamb after debauching his brother's wife. But Atreus was not restrained by prudence from retaliating, but contrived the slaughter of the children of Thyestes and the banquet of which the poets tell us.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>But as to what followed, I cannot say for certain whether Aegisthus began the sin or whether Agamemnon sinned first in murdering Tantalus, the son of Thyestes. It is said that Tantalus had received Clytaemnestra in marriage from Tyndareus when she was still a virgin. I myself do not wish to condemn them of having been wicked by nature; but if the pollution of Pelops and the avenging spirit of Myirtilus dogged their steps so long, it was after all only consistent that the Pythian priestess said to the Spartan Glaucus, the son of Epicydes, who consulted her about breaking his oath, that the punishment for this also comes upon the descendants of the sinner.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />A little beyond the Rams—this is the name they give to the tomb of Thyestes—there is on the left a place called <placeName key="tgn,7016748" authname="tgn,7016748">Mysia</placeName> and a sanctuary of Mysian Demeter, so named from a man Mysius who, say the Argives, was one of those who entertained Demeter. Now this sanctuary has no roof, but in it is another temple, built of burnt brick, and wooden images of the Maid, Pluto and Demeter. Farther on is a river called Inachus, and on the other side of it an altar of Helius （the Sun）. After this you will come to a gate named after the sanctuary near it. This sanctuary belongs to Eileithyia.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>The Argives are the only Greeks that I know of who have been divided into three kingdoms. For in the reign of Anaxagoras, son of Argeus, son of Megapenthes, the women were smitten with madness, and straying from their homes they roamed about the country, until Melampus the son of Amythaon cured them of the plague on condition that he himself and his brother Bias had a share of the kingdom equal to that of Anaxagoras. Now descended from Bias five men, Neleids on their mother's side, occupied the throne for four generations down to Cyanippus, son of Aegialeus, and descended from Melampus six men in six generations down to Amphilochus, son of Amphiaraus.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>But the native house of the family of Anaxagoras ruled longer than the other two. For Iphis, son of Alector, son of Anaxagoras, left the throne to Sthenelus, son of Capaneus his brother. After the capture of <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, Amphilochus migrated to the people now called the Amphilochians, and, Cyanippus having died without issue, Cylarabes, son of Sthenelus, became sole king. However, he too left no offspring, and <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> was seized by Orestes, son of Agamemnon, who was a neighbor. Besides his ancestral dominion, he had extended his rule over the greater part of <placeName key="tgn,7002735" authname="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName> and had succeeded to the throne of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta" authname="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>; he also had a contingent of Phocian allies always ready to help him.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>When Orestes became king of the Lacedaemonians, they themselves consented to accept him for they considered that the sons of the daughter of Tyndareus had a claim to the throne prior to that of Nicostratus and Megapenthes, who were sons of Menelaus by a slave woman. On the death of Orestes, there succeeded to the throne Tisamenus, the son of Orestes and of <placeName key="perseus,Hermione" authname="perseus,Hermione">Hermione</placeName>, the daughter of Menelaus. The mother of Penthilus, the bastard son of Orestes, was, according to the poet Cinaethon, Erigone, the daughter of Aegisthus.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>It was in the reign of this Tisamenus that the Heracleidae returned to the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>; they were Temenus and Cresphontes, the sons of Aristomachus, together with the sons of the third brother, Aristodemus, who had died. Their claim to <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> and to the throne of <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> was, in my opinion, most just, because Tisamenus was descended from Pelops, but the Heracleidae were descendants of Perseus. Tyndareus himself, they made out, had been expelled by Hippocoon, and they said that Heracles, having killed Hippocoon and his sons, had given the land in trust to Tyndareus. They gave the same kind of account about <placeName key="tgn,7011369" authname="tgn,7011369">Messenia</placeName> also, that it had been given in trust to Nestor by Heracles after he had taken Pylus.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p>So they expelled Tisamenus from <placeName key="tgn,7011065" authname="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, and the descendants of Nestor from <placeName key="tgn,7011369" authname="tgn,7011369">Messenia</placeName>, namely Alcmaeon, son of Sillus, son of Thrasymedes, Peisistratus, son of Peisistratus, and the sons of Paeon, son of Antilochus, and with them Melanthus, son of Andropompus, son of Borus, son of Penthilus, son of Periclymenus. So Tisamenus and his sons went with his army to the land that is now <placeName key="tgn,7002733" authname="tgn,7002733">Achaia</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="9" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />To what people Peisistratus retreated I do not know, but the rest of the Neleidae went to <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and the clans of the Paeonidae and of the Alcmaeonidae were named after them. Melanthus even came to the throne, having deposed Thymoetes the son of Oxyntes; for Thymoetes was the last Athenian king descended from Theseus.</p>
<milestone n="19" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />It is not to my purpose that I should set forth here the history of Cresphontes and of the sons of Aristodemus. But Temenus openly employed, instead of his sons, Delphontes, son of Antimachus, son of Thrasyanor, son of Ctesippus, son of Heracles, as general in war and as adviser on all occasions. Even before this he had made him his son-in-law, while Hyrnetho was his favorite daughter; he was accordingly suspected of intending to divert the throne to her and Delphontes. For this reason his sons plotted against him, and Ceisus, the eldest of them, seized the kingdom.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>But from the earliest times the Argives have loved freedom and self-government, and they limited to the utmost the authority of their kings, so that to Medon, the son of Ceisus, and to his descendants was left a kingdom that was such only in name. Meltas, the son of Lacedas, the tenth descendant of Medon, was condemned by the people and deposed altogether from the kingship.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>The most famous building in the city of <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> is the sanctuary of Apollo Lycius （Wolf-god）. The modern image was made by the Athenian Attalus,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">A sculptor of unknown date</note> but the original temple and wooden image were the offering of Danaus. I am of opinion that in those days all images, especially Egyptian images, were made of wood. The reason why Danaus founded a sanctuary of Apollo Lycius was this. On coming to <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> he claimed the kingdom against Gelanor, the son of Sthenelas. Many plausible arguments were brought forward by both parties, and those of Sthenelas were considered as fair as those of his opponent; so the people, who were sitting in judgment, put off, they say, the decision to the following day.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>At dawn a wolf fell upon a herd of oxen that was pasturing before the wall, and attacked and fought with the bull that was the leader of the herd. It occurred to the Argives that Gelanor was like the bull and Danaus like the wolf, for as the wolf will not live with men, so Danaus up to that time had not lived with them. It was because the wolf overcame the bull that Danaus won the kingdom. Accordingly, believing that Apollo had brought the wolf on the herd, he founded a sanctuary of Apollo Lycius.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>Here is dedicated the throne of Danaus, and here Is placed a statue of Biton, in the form of a man carrying a bull on his shoulders. According to the poet Lyceas, when the Argives were holding a sacrifice to Zeus at <placeName key="perseus,Nemea" authname="perseus,Nemea">Nemea</placeName>, Biton by sheer physical strength took up a bull and carried it there. Next to this statue is a fire which they keep burning, calling it the fire of Phoroneus. For they do not admit that fire was given to mankind by Prometheus, but insist in assigning the discovery of fire to Phoroneus.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>As to the wooden images of Aphrodite and Hermes, the one they say was made by Epeus, while the other is a votive offering of Hypermnestra. She was the only one of the daughters of Danaus who neglected his command,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">To kill their husbands.</note> and was accordingly brought to justice by him, because be considered that his life was in danger so long as Lynceus was at large, and that the refusal to share in the crime of her sisters increased the disgrace of the contriver of the deed. On her trial she was acquitted by the Argives, and to commemorate her escape she dedicated an image of Aphrodite, the Bringer of Victory.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Within the temple is a statue of Ladas, the swiftest runner of his time, and one of Hermes with a tortoise which he has caught to make a lyre. Before the temple is a pit<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Or （reading<foreign lang="greek">βάθρον πεποιημένην</foreign>and<foreign lang="greek">ἔχον</foreign>） “pedestal.”</note> with a relief representing a fight between a bull and a wolf, and with them a maiden throwing a rock at the bull. The maiden is thought to be Artemis. Danaus dedicated these, and some pillars hard by and wooden images of Zeus and Artemis.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Here are graves; one is that of Linus, the son of Apollo by Psamathe, the daughter of Crotopus; the other, they say, is that of Linus the poet. The story of the latter Linus is more appropriate to another part of my narrative, and so I omit it here, while I have already given the history of the son of Psamathe in my account of <placeName key="perseus,Megara" authname="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName>. After these is an image of Apollo, God of Streets, and an altar of Zeus, God of Rain, where those who were helping Polyneices in his efforts to be restored to <placeName key="perseus,Thebes" authname="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> swore an oath together that they would either capture <placeName key="perseus,Thebes" authname="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> or die. As to the tomb of Prometheus, their account seems to me to be less probable than that of the Opuntians,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">i.e. both peoples claimed to have the grave.</note> but they hold to it nevertheless.</p>
<milestone n="20" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Passing over a statue of Creugas, a boxer, and a trophy that was set up to celebrate a victory over the Corinthians, you come to a seated image of Zeus Meilichius （Gracious）, made of white marble by Polycleitus.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">c. <dateRange from="-480" to="-410" authname="-480/-410">480-410 B.C.</dateRange></note> I discovered that it was made for the following reason. Ever since the Lacedaemonians began to make war upon the Argives there was no cessation of hostilities until Philip, the son of Amyntas, forced them to stay within the original boundaries of their territories. Before this, if the Lacedaemonians were not engaged on some business outside the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>, they were always trying to annex a piece of <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> territory; or if they were busied with a war beyond their borders it was the turn of the Argives to retaliate.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>When the hatred of both sides was at its height, the Argives resolved to maintain a thousand picked men. The commander appointed over them was the Argive Bryas. His general behavior to the men of the people was violent, and a maiden who was being taken to the bridegroom he seized from those who were escorting her and ravished. When night came on, the girl waited until he was asleep and put out his eyes. Detected in the morning, she took refuge as a suppliant with the people. When they did not give her up to the Thousand for punishment both sides took up arms; the people won the day, and in their anger left none of their opponents alive.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><date value="-418" authname="-418">418 B.C.</date></note> Subsequently they had recourse to purifications for shedding kindred blood; among other things they dedicated an image of Zeus Meilichius.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>Hard by are Cleobis and Biton carved in relief on stone, themselves drawing the carriage and taking in it their mother to the sanctuary of Hera. Opposite them is a sanctuary of Nemean Zeus, and an upright bronze statue of the god made by Lysippus.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See p. 297.</note> Going forward from this you see on the right the grave of Phoroneus, to whom even in our time they bring offerings as to a hero. Over against the Nemean Zeus is a temple of Fortune, which must be very old if it be the one in which Palamedes dedicated the dice that he had invented.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>The tomb near this they call that of the maenad Chorea, saying that she was one of the women who joined Dionysus in his expedition against <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, and that Perseus, being victorious in the battle, put most of the women to the sword. To the rest they gave a common grave, but to Chorea they gave burial apart because of her high rank.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>A little farther on is a sanctuary of the Seasons. On coming back from here you see statues of Polyneices, the son of Oedipus, and of all the chieftains who with him were killed in battle at the wall of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes" authname="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>. These men Aeschylus has reduced to the number of seven only, although there were more chiefs than this in the expedition, from <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, from <placeName key="perseus,Messene" authname="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName>, with some even from <placeName key="tgn,7002735" authname="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName>. But the Argives have adopted the number seven from the drama of Aeschylus, and near to their statues are the statues of those who took <placeName key="perseus,Thebes" authname="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>: Aegialeus, son of Adrastus; Promachus, son of Parthenopaeus, son of Talaus; Polydorus, son of Hippomedon; Thersander; Alcmaeon and Amphilochus, the sons of Amphiaraus; Diomedes, and Sthenelus. Among their company were also Euryalus, son of Mecisteus, and Adrastus and Timeas, sons of Polyneices.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>Not far from the statues are shown the tomb of Danaus and a cenotaph of the Argives who met their death at <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> or on the journey home. Here there is also a sanctuary of Zeus the Saviour. Beyond it is a building where the <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> women bewail Adonis. On the right of the entrance is the sanctuary of Cephisus. It is said that the water of this river was not utterly destroyed by Poseidon, but that just in this place, where the sanctuary is, it can be heard flowing under the earth.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Beside the sanctuary of Cephisus is a head of Medusa made of stone, which is said to be another of the works of the Cyclopes. The ground behind it is called even at the present time the Place of Judgment, because it was here that they say Hypermnestra was brought to judgment by Danaus. Not far from this is a theater. In it are some noteworthy sights, including a representation of a man killing another, namely the Argive Perilaus, the son of Alcenor, killing the Spartan Othryadas. Before this, Perilaus had succeeded in winning the prize for wrestling at the Nemean games.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p>Above the theater is a sanctuary of Aphrodite, and before the image is a slab with a representation wrought on it in relief of Telesilla, the lyric poetess. Her books lie scattered at her feet, and she herself holds in her hand an helmet, which she is looking at and is about to place on her head. Telesilla was a distinguished woman who was especially renowned for her poetry. It happened that the Argives had suffered an awful defeat at the hands of Cleomenes, the son of Anaxandrides, and the Lacedaemonians. Some fell in the actual fighting; others, who had fled to the grove of Argus, also perished. At first they left sanctuary under an agreement, which was treacherously broken, and the survivors, when they realized this, were burnt to death in the grove. So when Cleomenes led his troops to <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> there were no men to defend it.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><date value="-510" authname="-510">510 B.C.</date></note></p>
<milestone n="9" unit="section" /><p>But Telesilla mounted on the wall all the slaves and such as were incapable of bearing arms through youth or old age, and she herself, collecting the arms in the sanctuaries and those that were left in the houses, armed the women of vigorous age, and then posted them where she knew the enemy would attack. When the Lacedaemonians came on, the women were not dismayed at their battle-cry, but stood their ground and fought valiantly. Then the Lacedaemonians, realizing that to destroy the women would be an invidious success while defeat would mean a shameful disaster, gave way before the women.</p>
<milestone n="10" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />This fight had been foretold by the Pythian priestess in the oracle quoted by Herodotus, who perhaps understood to what it referred and perhaps did not:—<quote type="oracle"><l met="dact">But when the time shall come that the female conquers in battle,</l><l>Driving away the male, and wins great glory in <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>,</l><l>Many an <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> woman will tear both cheeks in her sorrow.</l></quote><bibl n="Hdt. 6.77" default="NO" valid="yes">Hdt. 6.77</bibl>Such are the words of the oracle referring to the exploit of the women.</p>
<milestone n="21" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Having descended thence, and having turned again to the market-place, we come to the tomb of Cerdo, the wife of Phoroneus, and to a temple of Asclepius. The sanctuary of Artemis, surnamed Persuasion, is another offering of Hypermnestra after winning the trial to which she was brought by her father because of Lynceus. Here there is also a bronze statue of Aeneas, and a place called Delta. I intentionally do not discuss the origin of the name, because I could not accept the traditional accounts.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>In front of it stands an altar of Zeus Phyxius （God of Fight）, and near is the tomb of Hypermnestra, the mother of Amphiaraus, the other tomb being that of Hypermnestra, the daughter of Danaus, with whom is also buried Lynceus. Opposite these is the grave of Talaus, the son of Bias; the history of Bias and his descendants I have already given.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>A sanctuary of Athena Trumpet they say was founded by Hegeleos. This Hegeleos, according to the story, was the son of Tyrsenus, and Tyrsenus was the son of Heracles and the Lydian woman; Tyrsenus invented the trumpet, and Hegeleos, the son of Tyrsenus, taught the Dorians with Temenus how to play the instrument, and for this reason gave Athena the surname Trumpet. Before the temple of Athena is, they say, the grave of Epimenides. The <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> story is that the Lacedaemonians made war upon the Cnossians and took Epimenides alive; they then put him to death for not prophesying good luck to them, and the Argives taking his body buried it here.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>The building of white marble in just about the middle of the marketplace is not, as the Argives declare, a trophy in honor of a victory over Pyrrhus of Epeirus, but it can be shown that his body was burnt here, and that this is his monument, on which are carved in relief the elephants and his other instruments of warfare. This building then was set up where the pyre stood, but the bones of Pyrrhus lie in the sanctuary of Demeter, beside which, as I have shown in my account of <placeName key="tgn,7002681" authname="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>, his death occurred. At the entrance to this sanctuary of Demeter you can see a bronze shield of Pyrrhus hanging dedicated over the door.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>Not far from the building in the market-place of <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> is a mound of earth, in which they say lies the head of the Gorgon Medusa. I omit the miraculous, but give the rational parts of the story about her. After the death of her father, Phorcus, she reigned over those living around Lake Tritonis, going out hunting and leading the Libyans to battle. On one such occasion, when she was encamped with an army over against the forces of Perseus, who was followed by picked troops from the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>, she was assassinated by night. Perseus, admiring her beauty even in death, cut off her head and carried it to show the Greeks.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>But Procles, the son of Eucrates, a Carthaginian, thought a different account more plausible than the preceding. It is as follows. Among the incredible monsters to be found in the Libyan desert are wild men and wild women. Procles affirmed that he had seen a man from them who had been brought to <placeName key="perseus,Rome" authname="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. So he guessed that a woman wandered from them, reached Lake Tritonis, and harried the neighbours until Perseus killed her; Athena was supposed to have helped him in this exploit, because the people who live around Lake Tritonis are sacred to her.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>In <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, by the side of this monument of the Gorgon, is the grave of Gorgophone （Gorgon-kilIer）, the daughter of Perseus. As soon as you hear the name you can understand the reason why it was given her. On the death of her husband, Perieres, the son of Aeolus, whom she married when a virgin, she married Oebalus, being the first woman, they say, to marry a second time; for before this wives were wont, on the death of their husbands, to live as widows.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />In front of the grave is a trophy of stone made to commemorate a victory over an Argive Laphaes. When this man was tyrant I write what the Argives themselves say concerning themselves—the people rose up against him and cast him out. He fled to <placeName key="perseus,Sparta" authname="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, and the Lacedaemonians tried to restore him to power, but were defeated by the Argives, who killed the greater part of them and Laphaes as well.<milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Not far from the trophy is the sanctuary of Leto; the image is a work of Praxiteles.</p>
<milestone n="9" unit="section" /><p>The statue of the maiden beside the goddess they call Chloris （Pale）, saying that she was a daughter of Niobe, and that she was called <placeName key="perseus,Meliboea" authname="perseus,Meliboea">Meliboea</placeName> at the first. When the children of Amphion were destroyed by Apollo and Arternis, she alone of her sisters, along with Amyclas, escaped; their escape was due to their prayers to Leto. <placeName key="perseus,Meliboea" authname="perseus,Meliboea">Meliboea</placeName> was struck so pale by her fright, not only at the time but also for the rest of her life, that even her name was accordingly changed from <placeName key="perseus,Meliboea" authname="perseus,Meliboea">Meliboea</placeName> to Chloris.</p>
<milestone n="10" unit="section" /><p>Now the Argives say that these two built originally the temple to Leto, but I think that none of Niobe's children survived, for I place more reliance than others on the poetry of Homer, one of whose verses bears out my view:—<quote type="verse"><l met="dact">Though they were only two, yet they gave all to destruction.</l></quote><bibl n="Hom. Il. 24.609" default="NO" valid="yes">Hom. Il. 24.609</bibl>So Homer knows that the house of Amphion was utterly overthrown.</p>
<milestone n="22" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />The temple of Hera Anthea （Flowery） is on the right of the sanctuary of Leto, and before it is a grave of women. They were killed in a battle against the Argives under Perseus, having come from the <placeName key="tgn,7002674" authname="tgn,7002674">Aegean Islands</placeName> to help Dionysus in war; for which reason they are surnamed Haliae （Women of the Sea）. Facing the tomb of the women is a sanctuary of Demeter, surnamed Pelasgian from Pelasgus, son of Triopas, its founder, and not far from the sanctuary is the grave of Pelasgus.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>Opposite the grave is a small bronze vessel supporting ancient images of Artemis, Zeus, and Athena. Now Lyceas in his poem says that the image is of Zeus Mechaneus （Contriver）, and that here the Argives who set out against <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> swore to hold out in the war until they either took <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> or met their end fighting. Others have said that in the bronze vessel lie the bones of Tantalus.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>Now that the Tantalus is buried here who was the son of Thyestes or Broteas （both accounts are given） and married Clytaemnestra before Agamemnon did, I will not gainsay; but the grave of him who legend says was son of Zeus and Pluto—it is worth seeing—is on Mount Sipylus.  I know because I saw it. Moreover, no constraint came upon him to flee from Sipylus, such as afterwards forced Pelops to run away when Ilus the Phrygian launched an army against him.<milestone ed="P" unit="para" />But I must pursue the inquiry no further. The ritual performed at the pit hard by they say was instituted by Nicostratus, a native. Even at the present day they throw into the pit burning torches in honor of the Maid who is daughter of Demeter.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>Here is a sanctuary of Poseidon, surnamed Prosclystius （Flooder）, for they say that Poseidon inundated the greater part of the country because Inachus and his assessors decided that the land belonged to Hera and not to him. Now it was Hera who induced Poseidon to send the sea back, but the Argives made a sanctuary to Poseidon Prosclystius at the spot where the tide ebbed.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>Going on a little further you see the grave of Argus, reputed to be the son of Zeus and Niobe, daughter of Phoroneus. After these comes a temple of the Dioscuri. The images represent the Dioscuri themselves and their sons, Anaxis and Mnasinous, and with them are their mothers, Hilaeira and Phoebe. They are of ebony wood, and were made by Dipoenus and Scyllis.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Sixth cent. B.C.</note> The horses, too, are mostly of ebony, but there is a little ivory also in their construction.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>Near the Lords is a sanctuary of Eilethyia, dedicated by Helen when, Theseus having gone away with Peirithous to <placeName key="tgn,7002709" authname="tgn,7002709">Thesprotia</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Aphidna" authname="perseus,Aphidna">Aphidna</placeName> had been captured by the Dioscuri and Helen was being brought to <placeName key="tgn,7011065" authname="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName>. For it is said that she was with child, was delivered In Argos, and founded there the sanctuary of Eilethyia, giving the daughter she bore to Clytaemnestra, who was already wedded to Agamemnon, while she herself subsequently married Menelaus.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>And on this matter the poets Euphorion of <placeName key="perseus,Chalcis" authname="perseus,Chalcis">Chalcis</placeName> and Alexander of <placeName key="perseus,Pleuron" authname="perseus,Pleuron">Pleuron</placeName>, and even before them, Stesichorus of Himera, agree with the Argives in asserting that Iphigenia was the daughter of Theseus.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">c. <dateRange from="-610" to="-550" authname="-610/-550">610-550 B.C.</dateRange></note> Over against the sanctuary of Eilethyia is a temple of Hecate, and the image is a work of Scopas. This one is of stone, while the bronze images opposite, also of Hecate, were made respectively by Polycleitus<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">It is uncertain who this Polycleitus was or when he lived. He was not the great Polycleitus, and flourished probably after <date value="-400" authname="-400">400 B.C.</date></note> and his brother Naucydes, son of Mothon.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p>As you go along a straight road to a gymnasium, called Cylarabis after the son of Sthenelus, you come to the grave of Licymnius, the son of Electryon, who, Homer says, was killed by Tleptolemus, the son of Heracles for which homicide Tleptolemus was banished from <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>. On turning a little aside from the road to Cylarabis and to the gate there, you come to the tomb of Sacadas, who was the first to play at <placeName key="perseus,Delphi" authname="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName> the Pythian flute-tune;</p>
<milestone n="9" unit="section" /><p>the hostility of Apollo to flute-players, which had lasted ever since the rivalry of Marsyas the Silenus, is supposed to have stayed because of this Sacadas. In the gymnasium of Cylarabes is an Athena called Pania; they show also the graves of Sthenelus and of Cylarabes himself. Not far from the gymnasium has been built a common grave of those Argives who sailed with the Athenians to enslave <placeName key="perseus,Syracuse" authname="perseus,Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7003122" authname="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="23" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />As you go from here along a road called Hollow there is on the right a temple of Dionysus; the image, they say, is from <placeName key="tgn,7002677" authname="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>. For when the Greeks, as they were returning from <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, met with the shipwreck at Caphereus, those of the Argives who were able to escape to land suffered from cold and hunger. Having prayed that someone of the gods should prove himself a saviour in their present distress, straightway as they advanced they came upon a cave of Dionysus; in the cave was an image of the god, and on this occasion wild she-goats had gathered there to escape from the storm. These the Argives killed, using the flesh as food and the skins as raiment. When the storm was over and the Argives, having refitted their ships, were returning home, they took with them the wooden image from the cave, and continue to honor it to the present day.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>Very near to the temple of Dionysus you will see the house of Adrastus, farther on a sanctuary of Amphiaraus, and opposite the sanctuary the tomb of Eriphyle. Next to these is a precinct of Asclepius, and after them a sanctuary of Baton. Now Baton belonged to the same family as Amphiaraus, to the Melampodidae, and served as his charioteer when he went forth to battle. When the rout took place at the wall of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes" authname="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, the earth opened and received Amphiaraus and his chariot, swallowing up this Baton at the same time.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>Returning from Hollow Street, you see what they say is the grave of Hyrnetho. If they allow that it is merely a cenotaph erected to the memory of the lady, their account is likely enough but if they believe that the corpse lies here I cannot credit it, and leave anyone to do so who has not learnt the history of <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>The most famous sanctuary of Asclepius at <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> contains at the present day a white-marble image of the god seated, and by his side stands Health. There are also seated figures of Xenophilus and Straton, who made the images. The original founder of the sanctuary was Sphyrus, son of Machaon and brother of the Alexanor who is honored among the Sicyonians in <placeName key="perseus,Titane" authname="perseus,Titane">Titane</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>The Argives, like the Athenians and Sicyorians, worship Artemis Pheraea, and they, too, assert that the image of the goddess was brought from Pherae in <placeName key="tgn,7001399" authname="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName>. But I cannot agree with them when they say that in <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> are the tombs of Deianeira, the daughter of Oeneus, and of Helenus, son of Priam, and that there is among them the image of Athena that was brought from <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, thus causing the capture of that city. For the Palladium, as it is called, was manifestly brought to <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> by Aeneas. As to Deianeira, we know that her death took place near <placeName key="perseus,Trachis" authname="perseus,Trachis">Trachis</placeName> and not in <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, and her grave is near <placeName key="tgn,7008299" authname="tgn,7008299">Heraclea</placeName>, at the foot of Mount Oeta.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>The story of Helenus, son of Priam, I have already given: that he went to Epeirus with Pyrrhus, the son of. Achilles; that, wedded to Andromache, he was guardian to the children of Pyrrhus and that the district called <placeName key="perseus,Cestrine" authname="perseus,Cestrine">Cestrine</placeName> received its name from Cestrinus, son of Helenus. Now even the guides of the Argives themselves are aware that their account is not entirely correct. Nevertheless they hold to their opinion, for it is not easy to make the multitude change their views. The Argives have other things worth seeing;</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>for instance, an underground building over which was the bronze chamber which Acrisius once made to guard his daughter. Perilaus, however, when he became tyrant, pulled it down. Besides this building there is the tomb of Crotopus and a temple of Cretan Dionysus. For they say that the god, having made war on Perseus, afterwards laid aside his enmity, and received great honors at the hands of the Argives, including this precinct set specially apart for himself.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />It was afterwards called the precinct of the Cretan god, because, when Ariadne died, Dionysus buried her here. But Lyceas says that when the temple was being rebuilt an earthenware coffin was found, and that it was Ariadne's. He also said that both he himself and other Argives had seen it. Near the temple of Dionysus is a temple of Heavenly Aphrodite.</p>
<milestone n="24" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />The citadel they call <placeName key="tgn,7010894" authname="tgn,7010894">Larisa</placeName>, after the daughter of Pelasgus. After her were also named two of the cities in <placeName key="tgn,7001399" authname="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName>, the one by the sea and the one on the Peneus. As you go up the citadel you come to the sanctuary of Hera of the Height, and also a temple of Apollo, which is said to have been first built by Pythaeus when he came from <placeName key="perseus,Delphi" authname="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>. The present image is a bronze standing figure called Apollo Deiradiotes, because this place, too, is called Deiras （Ridge）. Oracular responses are still given here, and the oracle acts in the following way. There is a woman who prophesies, being debarred from intercourse with a man. Every month a lamb is sacrificed at night, and the woman, after tasting the blood, becomes inspired by the god.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>Adjoining the temple of Apollo Deiradiotes is a sanctuary of Athena Oxyderces （Sharp-sighted）, dedicated by Diomedes, because once when he was fighting at <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> the goddess removed the mist from his eyes. Adjoining it is the race-course, in which they hold the games in honor of Nemean Zeus and the festival of Hera. As you go to the citadel there is on the left of the road another tomb of the children of <placeName key="tgn,7016833" authname="tgn,7016833">Aegyptus</placeName>. For here are the heads apart from the bodies, which are at <placeName key="perseus,Lerna" authname="perseus,Lerna">Lerna</placeName>. For it was at <placeName key="perseus,Lerna" authname="perseus,Lerna">Lerna</placeName> that the youths were murdered, and when they were dead their wives cut off their heads, to prove to their father that they had done the dreadful deed.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>On the top of <placeName key="tgn,7010894" authname="tgn,7010894">Larisa</placeName> is a temple of Zeus, surnamed Larisaean, which has no roof; the wooden image I found no longer standing upon its pedestal. There is also a temple of Athena worth seeing. Here are placed votive offerings, including a wooden image of Zeus, which has two eyes in the natural place and a third on its forehead. This Zeus, they say, was a paternal god of Priam, the son of Laomedon, set up in the uncovered part of his court, and when <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> was taken by the Greeks Priam took sanctuary at the altar of this god. When the spoils were divided, Sthenelus, the son of Capaneus, received the image, and for this reason it has been dedicated here.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>The reason for its three eyes one might infer to be this. That Zeus is king in heaven is a saying common to all men. As for him who is said to rule under the earth, there is a verse of Homer which calls him, too, Zeus:—<milestone ed="P" unit="para" /><quote type="verse"><l met="dact">Zeus of the Underworld, and the august Persephonea.</l></quote><bibl n="Hom. Il. 9.457" default="NO" valid="yes">Hom. Il. 9.457</bibl>The god in the sea, also, is called Zeus by Aeschylus, the son of Euphorion. So whoever made the image made it with three eyes, as signifying that this same god rules in all the three “allotments” of the Universe, as they are called.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>From <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> are roads to various parts of the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>, including one to Teges on the side towards <placeName key="tgn,7002735" authname="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName>. On the right is Mount Lycone, which has trees on it, chiefly cypresses. On the top of the mountain is built a sanctuary of Artemis Orthia （of the Steep）, and there have been made white-marble images of Apollo, Leto, and Artemis, which they say are works of Polycleitus. On descending again from the mountain you see on the left of the highway a temple of Artemis.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>A little farther on there is on the right of the road a mountain called Chaon. At its foot grow cultivated trees, and here the water of the Erasinus rises to the surface. Up to this point it flows from Stymphalus in <placeName key="tgn,7002735" authname="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName>, just as the Rheiti, near the sea at <placeName key="perseus,Eleusis" authname="perseus,Eleusis">Eleusis</placeName>, flow from the Euripus. At the places where the Erasinus gushes forth from the mountain they sacrifice to Dionysus and to Pan, and to Dionysus they also hold a festival called Tyrbe （Throng）.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />On returning to the road that leads to <placeName key="perseus,Tegea" authname="perseus,Tegea">Tegea</placeName> you see Cenchreae on the right of what is called the Wheel. Why the place received this name they do not say. Perhaps in this case also it was Cenchrias, son of Peirene, that caused it to be so called. Here are common graves of the Argives who conquered the Lacedaemonians in battle at Hysiae.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">669-8 B.C.</note> This fight took place, I discovered, when Peisistratus was archon at <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, in the fourth year of the twenty-seventh Olympiad, in which the Athenian, Eurybotus, won the foot-race. On coming down to a lower level you reach the ruins of Hysiae, which once was a city in <placeName key="tgn,7002739" authname="tgn,7002739">Argolis</placeName>, and here it is that they say the Lacedaemonians suffered their reverse.</p>
<milestone n="25" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />The road from <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> to <placeName key="perseus,Mantinea" authname="perseus,Mantinea">Mantinea</placeName> is not the same as that to <placeName key="perseus,Tegea" authname="perseus,Tegea">Tegea</placeName>, but begins from the gate at the Ridge. On this road is a sanctuary built with two rooms, having an entrance on the west side and another on the east. At the latter is a wooden image of Aphrodite, and at the west entrance one of Ares. They say that the images are votive offerings of Polyneices and of the Argives who joined him in the campaign to redress his wrongs.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>Farther on from here, across the torrent called Charadrus （Gully）, is Oenoe, named, the Argives say, after Oeneus. The story is that Oeneus, who was king in <placeName key="tgn,7002678" authname="tgn,7002678">Aetolia</placeName>, on being driven from his throne by the sons of Agrius, took refuge with Diomedes at <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, who aided him by an expedition into Calydonia, but said that he could not remain with him, and urged Oeneus to accompany him, if he wished, to <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>. When he came, he gave him all the attention that it was right to give a father's father, and on his death buried him here. After him the Argives name the place Oenoe.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>Above Oenoe is Mount Artemisius, with a sanctuary of Artemis on the top. On this mountain are also the springs of the river Inachus. For it really has springs, though the water does not run far.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>Here I found nothing else that is worth seeing.  There is another road, that leads to Lyrcea from the gate at the Ridge. The story is that to this place came Lynceus, being the only one of the fifty brothers to escape death, and that on his escape he raised a beacon here. Now to raise the beacon was the signal he had agreed with Hypermnestra to give if he should escape Danaus and reach a place of safety. She also, they say, lighted a beacon on <placeName key="tgn,7010894" authname="tgn,7010894">Larisa</placeName> as a sign that she too was now out of danger. For this reason the Argives hold every year a beacon festival.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>At the first the place was called Lyncea; its present name is derived from Lyrcus, a bastard son of Abas, who afterwards dwelt there. Among the ruins are several things not worth mentioning, besides a figure of Lyrcus upon a slab. The distance from <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> to Lyrcea is about sixty stades, and the distance from Lyrcea to Orneae is the same. Homer in the Catalogue makes no mention of the city Lyrcea, because at the time of the Greek expedition against <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> it already lay deserted; Omeae, however, was inhabited, and in his poem he places it<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 2.571" default="NO" valid="yes">Hom. Il. 2.571</bibl></note> on the list before Phlius and <placeName key="tgn,7011098" authname="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName>, which order corresponds to the position of the towns in the <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> territory.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />The name is derived from Orneus, the son of Erechtheus. This Orneus begat Peteos, and Peteos begat Menestheus, who, with a body of Athenians, helped Agamemnon to destroy the kingdom of Priam. From him then did Omeae get its name, and afterwards the Argives removed all its citizens, who thereupon came to live at <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>. At Orneae are a sanctuary and an upright wooden image of Artemis; there is besides a temple devoted to all the gods in common. On the further side of Orneae are Sicyonia and Phliasia.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />On the way from <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> to Epidauria there is on the right a building made very like a pyramid, and on it in relief are wrought shields of the <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> shape. Here took place a fight for the throne between Proetus and Acrisius; the contest, they say, ended in a draw, and a reconciliation resulted afterwards, as neither could gain a decisive victory. The story is that they and their hosts were armed with shields, which were first used in this battle. For those that fell on either side was built here a common tomb, as they were fellow citizens and kinsmen.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p>Going on from here and turning to the right, you come to the ruins of <placeName key="perseus,Tiryns" authname="perseus,Tiryns">Tiryns</placeName>. The Tirynthians also were removed by the Argives, who wished to make <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> more powerful by adding to the population. The hero <placeName key="perseus,Tiryns" authname="perseus,Tiryns">Tiryns</placeName>, from whom the city derived its name, is said to have been a son of Argus, a son of Zeus. The wall, which is the only part of the ruins still remaining, is a work of the Cyclopes made of unwrought stones, each stone being so big that a pair of mules could not move the smallest from its place to the slightest degree. Long ago small stones were so inserted that each of them binds the large blocks firmly together.</p>
<milestone n="9" unit="section" /><p>Going down seawards, you come to the chambers of the daughters of Proetus. On returning to the highway you will reach Medea on the left hand. They say that Electryon, the father of Alcmena, was king of Medea, but in my time nothing was left of it except the foundations.</p>
<milestone n="10" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />On the straight road to <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName> is a village <placeName key="perseus,Lessa" authname="perseus,Lessa">Lessa</placeName>, in which is a temple of Athena with a wooden image exactly like the one on the citadel <placeName key="tgn,7010894" authname="tgn,7010894">Larisa</placeName>. Above <placeName key="perseus,Lessa" authname="perseus,Lessa">Lessa</placeName> is Mount Arachnaeus, which long ago, in the time of Inachus, was named Sapyselaton.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See the Greek text, in which the name Sapyselaton is formed from the two words<foreign lang="greek">σάπυς ἐλάτων</foreign>.</note> On it are altars to Zeus and Hera. When rain is needed they sacrifice to them here.</p>
<milestone n="26" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />At <placeName key="perseus,Lessa" authname="perseus,Lessa">Lessa</placeName> the <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> territory joins that of <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName>. But before you reach <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName> itself you will come to the sanctuary of Asclepius. Who dwelt in this land before <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName> came to it I do not know, nor could I discover from the natives the descendants of <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName> either. But the last king before the Dorians arrived in the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName> was, they say, Pityreus, a descendant of Ion, son of Xuthus, and they relate that he handed over the land to Deiphontes and the Argives without a struggle.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>He went to <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> with his people and dwelt there, while Deiphontes and the Argives took possession of Epidauria. These on the death of Temenus seceded from the other Argives; Deiphontes and Hyrnetho through hatred of the sons of Temenus, and the army with them, because it respected Deiphontes and Hyrnetho more than Ceisus and his brothers. Epidaurus, who gave the land its name, was, the Eleans say, a son of Pelops but, according to <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> opinion and the poem the <title>Great Eoeae</title>,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">A poem attributed to Hesiod.</note> the father of <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName> was Argus, son of Zeus, while the Epidaurians maintain that <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName> was the child of Apollo.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>That the land is especially sacred to Asclepius is due to the following reason. The Epidaurians say that Phlegyas came to the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>, ostensibly to see the land, but really to spy out the number of the inhabitants, and whether the greater part of them was warlike. For Phlegyas was the greatest soldier of his time, and making forays in all directions he carried off the crops and lifted the cattle.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>When he went to the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>, he was accompanied by his daughter, who all along had kept hidden from her father that she was with child by Apollo. In the country of the Epidaurians she bore a son, and exposed him on the mountain called Nipple at the present day, but then named Myrtium. As the child lay exposed he was given milk by one of the goats that pastured about the mountain, and was guarded by the watch-dog of the herd. And when Aresthanas （for this was the herdsman's name）</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>discovered that the tale of the goats was not full, and that the watch-dog also was absent from the herd, he left, they say, no stone unturned, and on finding the child desired to take him up. As he drew near he saw lightning that flashed from the child, and, thinking that it was something divine, as in fact it was, he turned away. Presently it was reported over every land and sea that Asclepius was discovering everything he wished to heal the sick, and that he was raising dead men to life.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>There is also another tradition concerning him. Coronis, they say, when with child with Asclepius, had intercourse with Ischys, son of Elatus. She was killed by Artemis to punish her for the insult done to Apollo, but when the pyre was already lighted Hermes is said to have snatched the child from the flames.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>The third account is, in my opinion, the farthest from the truth; it makes Asclepius to be the son of <placeName key="tgn,7016892" authname="tgn,7016892">Arsinoe</placeName>, the daughter of Leucippus. For when Apollophanes the Arcadian, came to <placeName key="perseus,Delphi" authname="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName> and asked the god if Asclepius was the son of <placeName key="tgn,7016892" authname="tgn,7016892">Arsinoe</placeName> and therefore a Messenian, the Pythian priestess gave this response:—<quote type="oracle"><l met="dact">0 Asclepius, born to bestow great joy upon mortals,</l><l>Pledge of the mutual love I enjoyed with Phlegyas' daughter,</l><l>Lovely Coronis, who bare thee in rugged land <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName>.</l></quote><bibl default="NO">Unknown</bibl>. This oracle makes it quite certain that Asclepius was not a son of <placeName key="tgn,7016892" authname="tgn,7016892">Arsinoe</placeName>, and that the story was a fiction invented by Hesiod, or by one of Hesiod's interpolators, just to please the Messenians.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p>There is other evidence that the god was born in <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName> for I find that the most famous sanctuaries of Asclepius had their origin from <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName>. In the first place, the Athenians, who say that they gave a share of their mystic rites to Asclepius, call this day of the festival Epidauria, and they allege that their worship of Asclepius dates from then. Again, when Archias, son of Aristaechmus, was healed in Epidauria after spraining himself while hunting about Pindasus, he brought the cult to <placeName key="tgn,7016140" authname="tgn,7016140">Pergamus</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="9" unit="section" /><p>From the one at <placeName key="tgn,7016140" authname="tgn,7016140">Pergamus</placeName> has been built in our own day the sanctuary of Asclepius by the sea at <placeName key="perseus,Smyrna" authname="perseus,Smyrna">Smyrna</placeName>. Further, at Balagrae of the Cyreneans there is an Asclepius called Healer, who like the others came from <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName>. From the one at <placeName key="tgn,7000639" authname="tgn,7000639">Cyrene</placeName> was founded the sanctuary of Asclepius at Lebene, in <placeName key="tgn,7012056" authname="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>. There is this difference between the Cyreneans and the Epidaurians, that whereas the former sacrifice goats, it is against the custom of the Epidaurians to do so.</p>
<milestone n="10" unit="section" /><p>That Asclepius was considered a god from the first, and did not receive the title only in course of time, I infer from several signs, including the evidence of Homer, who makes Agamemnon say about Machaon:—<quote type="verse"><l met="dact">Talthybius, with all speed go summon me hither Machaon,</l><l>Mortal son of Asclepius.</l></quote><bibl n="Hom. Il. 4.193" default="NO" valid="yes">Hom. Il. 4.193</bibl>As who should say, “human son of a god.”</p>
<milestone n="27" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />The sacred grove of Asclepius is surrounded on all sides by boundary marks. No death or birth takes place within the enclosure the same custom prevails also in the island of <placeName key="perseus,Delos" authname="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName>. All the offerings, whether the offerer be one of the Epidaurians themselves or a stranger, are entirely consumed within the bounds. At <placeName key="perseus,Titane" authname="perseus,Titane">Titane</placeName> too, I know, there is the same rule.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>The image of Asclepius is, in size, half as big as the Olympian Zeus at <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and is made of ivory and gold. An inscription tells us that the artist was Thrasymedes, a Parian, son of Arignotus. The god is sitting on a seat grasping a staff; the other hand he is holding above the head of the serpent; there is also a figure of a dog lying by his side. On the seat are wrought in relief the exploits of <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> heroes, that of Bellerophontes against the Chimaera, and Perseus, who has cut off the head of Medusa. Over against the temple is the place where the suppliants of the god sleep.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>Near has been built a circular building of white marble, called Tholos （Round House）, which is worth seeing. In it is a picture by Pausias<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">1. A famous painter of <placeName key="tgn,7011098" authname="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName>.</note> representing Love, who has cast aside his bow and arrows, and is carrying instead of them a lyre that he has taken up. Here there is also another work of Pausias, Drunkenness drinking out of a crystal cup. You can see even in the painting a crystal cup and a woman's face through it. Within the enclosure stood slabs; in my time six remained, but of old there were more. On them are inscribed the names of both the men and the women who have been healed by Asclepius, the disease also from which each suffered, and the means of cure. The dialect is Doric.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>Apart from the others is an old slab, which declares that Hippolytus dedicated twenty horses to the god. The Aricians tell a tale that agrees with the inscription on this slab, that when Hippolytus was killed, owing to the curses of Theseus, Asclepius raised him from the dead. On coming to life again he refused to forgive his father rejecting his prayers, he went to the Aricians in <placeName key="tgn,1000080" authname="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>. There he became king and devoted a precinct to Artemis, where down to my time the prize for the victor in single combat was the priesthood of the goddess. The contest was open to no freeman, but only to slaves who had run away from their masters.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>The Epidaurians have a theater within the sanctuary, in my opinion very well worth seeing. For while the Roman theaters are far superior to those anywhere else in their splendor, and the Arcadian theater at <placeName key="perseus,Megalopolis" authname="perseus,Megalopolis">Megalopolis</placeName> is unequalled for size, what architect could seriously rival Polycleitus in symmetry and beauty? For it was Polycleitus<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Probably the younger artist of that name.</note> who built both this theater and the circular building. Within the grove are a temple of Artemis, an image of Epione, a sanctuary of Aphrodite and Themis, a race-course consisting, like most Greek race-courses, of a bank of earth, and a fountain worth seeing for its roof and general splendour.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>A Roman senator, Antoninus, made in our own day a bath of Asclepius and a sanctuary of the gods they call Bountiful.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><date value="138" authname="138">138</date> or <date value="161" authname="161">161 A.D.</date></note> He made also a temple to Health, Asclepius, and Apollo, the last two surnamed Egyptian. He moreover restored the portico that was named the Portico of Cotys, which, as the brick of which it was made had been unburnt, had fallen into utter ruin after it had lost its roof. As the Epidaurians about the sanctuary were in great distress, because their women had no shelter in which to be delivered and the sick breathed their last in the open, he provided a dwelling, so that these grievances also were redressed. Here at last was a place in which without sin a human being could die and a woman be delivered.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Above the grove are the Nipple and another mountain called Cynortium; on the latter is a sanctuary of Maleatian Apollo. The sanctuary itself is an ancient one, but among the things Antoninus made for the Epidaurians are various appurtenances for the sanctuary of the Maleatian, including a reservoir into which the rain-water collects for their use.</p>
<milestone n="28" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />The serpents, including a peculiar kind of a yellowish color, are considered sacred to Asclepius, and are tame with men. These are peculiar to Epidauria, and I have noticed that other lands have their peculiar animals. For in <placeName key="tgn,1000172" authname="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName> only are to be found land crocodiles at least two cubits long; from <placeName key="tgn,7000198" authname="tgn,7000198">India</placeName> alone are brought, among other creatures, parrots. But the big snakes that grow to more than thirty cubits, such as are found in <placeName key="tgn,7000198" authname="tgn,7000198">India</placeName> and in <placeName key="tgn,1000172" authname="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName>, are said by the Epidaurians not to be serpents, but some other kind of creature.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>As you go up to Mount Coryphum you see by the road an olive tree called Twisted. It was Heracles who gave it this shape by bending it round with his hand, but I cannot say whether he set it to be a boundary mark against the Asinaeans in <placeName key="tgn,7002739" authname="tgn,7002739">Argolis</placeName>, since in no land, which has been depopulated, is it easy to discover the truth about the boundaries. On the Top of the mountain there is a sanctuary of Artemis Coryphaea （of the Peak）, of which Telesilla<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">A famous lyric poetess. See p. 355.</note> made mention in an ode.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>On going down to the city of the Epidaurians, you come to a place where wild olives grow; they call it Hyrnethium. I will relate the story of it, which is probable enough, as given by the Epidaurians. Ceisus and the other sons of Temenus knew that they would grieve Deiphontes most if they could find a way to part him and Hyrnetho. So Cerynes and Phalces （for Agraeus, the youngest, disapproved of their plan） came to <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName>. Staying their chariot under the wall, they sent a herald to their sister, pretending that they wished to parley with her.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>When she obeyed their summons, the young men began to make many accusations against Deiphontes, and besought her much that she would return to <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, promising, among other things, to give her to a husband in every respect better than Deiphontes, one who ruled over more subjects and a more prosperous country. But Hyrnetho, pained at their words, gave as good as she had received, retorting that Deiphontes was a dear husband to her, and had shown himself a blameless son-in-law to Temenus; as for them, they ought to be called the murderers of Temenus rather than his sons.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>Without further reply the youths seized her, placed her in the chariot, and drove away. An Epidaurian told Deiphontes that Cerynes and Phalces had gone, taking with them Hyrnetho against her will; he himself rushed to the rescue with all speed, and as the Epidaurians learned the news they reinforced him. On overtaking the runaways, Deiphontes shot Cerynes and killed him, but he was afraid to shoot at Phalces, who was holding Hyrnetho, lest he should miss him and become the slayer of his wife; so he closed with them and tried to get her away. But Phalces, holding on and dragging her with greater violence, killed her, as she was with child.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>Realizing what he had done to his sister, he began to drive the chariot more recklessly, as he was anxious to gain a start before all the Epidaurians could gather against him. Deiphontes and his children—for before this children had been born to him, Antimenes, Xanthippus, and Argeus, and a daughter, Orsobia, who, they say, after-wards married Pamphylus, son of Aegimius—took up the dead body of Hyrnetho and carried it to this place, which in course of time was named Hyrnethium.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />They built for her a hero-shrine, and bestowed upon her various honors; in particular, the custom was established that nobody should carry home, or use for any purpose, the pieces that break off the olive trees, or any other trees, that grow there; these are left there on the spot to be sacred to Hyrnetho.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Not far from the city is the tomb of <placeName key="perseus,Melissa" authname="perseus,Melissa">Melissa</placeName>, who married Periander, the son of Cypselus, and another of Procles, the father of Melissa. He, too, was tyrant of <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName>, as Periander, his son-in-law, was tyrant of <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">c. <date value="-600" authname="-600">600 B.C.</date></note></p>
<milestone n="29" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />The most noteworthy things which I found the city of <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName> itself had to show are these. There is, of course, a precinct of Asclepius, with images of the god himself and of Epione. Epione, they say, was the wife of Asclepius. These are of Parian marble, and are set up in the open. There is also in the city a temple of Dionysus and one of Artemis. The figure of Artemis one might take to be the goddess hunting. There is also a sanctuary of Aphrodite, while the one at the harbor, on a height that juts out into the sea, they say is Hera's. The Athena on the citadel, a wooden image worth seeing, they surname Cissaea （Ivy Goddess）.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>The Aeginetans dwell in the island over against Epidauria. It is said that in the beginning there were no men in it; but after Zeus brought to it, when uninhabited, <placeName key="tgn,7011087" authname="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName>, daughter of Asopus, its name was changed from Oenone to <placeName key="tgn,7011087" authname="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName>; and when Aeacus, on growing up, asked Zeus for settlers, the god, they say, raised up the inhabitants out of the earth. They can mention no king of the island except Aeacus, since we know of none even of the sons of Aeacus who stayed there; for to Peleus and Telamon befell exile for the murder of Phocus, while the sons of Phocus made their home about <placeName key="tgn,7011022" authname="tgn,7011022">Parnassus</placeName>, in the land that is now called <placeName key="tgn,4003963" authname="tgn,4003963">Phocis</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>This name had already been given to the land, at the time when Phocus, son of Ornytion, came to it a generation previously. In the time, then, of this Phocus only the district about <placeName key="perseus,Tithorea" authname="perseus,Tithorea">Tithorea</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7011022" authname="tgn,7011022">Parnassus</placeName> was called <placeName key="tgn,4003963" authname="tgn,4003963">Phocis</placeName>, but in the time of Aeacus the name spread to all from the borders of the Minyae at <placeName key="perseus,Orchomenos" authname="perseus,Orchomenos">Orchomenos</placeName> to Scarphea among the <placeName key="perseus,Locri" authname="perseus,Locri">Locri</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>From Peleus sprang the kings in Epeirus; but as for the sons of Telamon, the family of Ajax is undistinguished, because he was a man who lived a private life; though Miltiades, who led the Athenians to Marathon,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><date value="-490" authname="-490">490 B.C.</date></note> and Cimon, the son of Miltiades, achieved renown; but the family of Teucer continued to be the royal house in <placeName key="tgn,1000112" authname="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName> down to the time of Evagoras. Asius the epic poet says that to Phocus were born Panopeus and Crisus. To Panopeus was born Epeus, who made, according to Homer, the wooden horse; and the grandson of Crisus was Pylades, whose father was Strophius, son of Crisus, while his mother was Anaxibi ,sister of Agamemnon. Such was the pedigree of the Aeacidae （family of. Aeacus）, as they are called, but they departed from the beginning to other lands.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Subsequently a division of the Argives who, under Deiphontes, had seized <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName>, crossed to <placeName key="tgn,7011087" authname="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName>, and, settling among the old Aeginetans, established in the island Dorian manners and the Dorian dialect. Although the Aeginetans rose to great power, so that their navy was superior to that of <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and in the Persian war supplied more ships than any state except <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, yet their prosperity was not permanent but when the island was depopulated by the Athenians,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><date value="-431" authname="-431">431 B.C.</date></note> they took up their abode at Thyrea, in <placeName key="tgn,7002739" authname="tgn,7002739">Argolis</placeName>, which the Lacedaemonians gave them to dwell in. They recovered their island when the Athenian warships were captured in the <placeName key="tgn,7002638" authname="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName>,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><date value="-405" authname="-405">405 B.C.</date></note> yet it was never given them to rise again to their old wealth or power.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>Of the Greek islands, <placeName key="tgn,7011087" authname="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName> is the most difficult of access, for it is surrounded by sunken rocks and reefs which rise up. The story is that Aeacus devised this feature of set purpose, because he feared piratical raids by sea, and wished the approach to be perilous to enemies. Near the harbor in which vessels mostly anchor is a temple of Aphrodite, and in the most conspicuous part of the city what is called the shrine of Aeacus, a quadrangular enclosure of white marble.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>Wrought in relief at the entrance are the envoys whom the Greeks once dispatched to Aeacus. The reason for the embassy given by the Aeginetans is the same as that which the other Greeks assign. A drought had for some time afflicted <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, and no rain fell either beyond the Isthmus or in the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>, until at last they sent envoys to <placeName key="perseus,Delphi" authname="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName> to ask what was the cause and to beg for deliverance from the evil. The Pythian priestess bade them propitiate Zeus, saying that he would not listen to them unless the one to supplicate him were Aeacus.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p>And so envoys came with a request to Aeacus from each city. By sacrifice and prayer to Zeus, God of all the Greeks （Panellenios）, he caused rain to fall upon the earth, and the Aeginetans made these likenesses of those who came to him. Within the enclosure are olive trees that have grown there from of old, and there is an altar which is raised but a little from the ground. That this altar is also the tomb of Aeacus is told as a holy secret.</p>
<milestone n="9" unit="section" /><p>Beside the shrine of Aeacus is the grave of Phocus, a barrow surrounded by a basement, and on it lies a rough stone. When Telamon and Peleus had induced Phocus to compete at the pentathlon, and it was now the turn of Peleus to hurl the stone, which they were using for a quoit, he intentionally hit Phocus. The act was done to please their mother; for, while they were both born of the daughter of Sciron, Phocus was not, being, if indeed the report of the Greeks be true, the son of a sister of Thetis. I believe it was for this reason, and not only out of friendship for Orestes, that Pylades plotted the murder of Neoptolemus.</p>
<milestone n="10" unit="section" /><p>When this blow of the quoit killed Phocus, the sons of Endeis boarded a ship and fled. Afterwards Telamon sent a herald denying that he had plotted the death of Phocus. Aeacus, however, refused to allow him to land on the island, and bade him make his defence standing on board ship, or if he wished, from a mole raised in the sea. So he sailed into the harbor called Secret, and proceeded to make a mole by night. This was finished, and still remains at the present day. But Telamon, being condemned as implicated in the murder of Phocus, sailed away a second time and came to <placeName key="tgn,7002340" authname="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="11" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Not far from the Secret Harbor is a theater worth seeing; it is very similar to the one at <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName>, both in size and in style. Behind it is built one side of a race-course, which not only itself holds up the theater, but also in turn uses it as a support.</p>
<milestone n="30" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />There are three temples close together, one of Apollo, one of Artemis, and a third of Dionysus. Apollo has a naked wooden image of native workmanship, but Artemis is dressed, and so, too, is Dionysus, who is, moreover, represented with a beard. The sanctuary of Asclepius is not here, but in another place, and his image is of stone, and seated.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>Of the gods, the Aeginetans worship most Hecate, in whose honor every year they celebrate mystic rites which, they say, Orpheus the Thracian established among them. Within the enclosure is a temple; its wooden image is the work of Myron,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">fl. c. <date value="-460" authname="-460">460 B.C.</date></note> and it has one face and one body. It was Alcamenes,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">A contemporary of Pheidias.</note> in my opinion, who first made three images of Hecate attached to one another, a figure called by the Athenians Epipurgidia （on the Tower）; it stands beside the temple of the Wingless Victory.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>In <placeName key="tgn,7011087" authname="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName>, as you go towards the mountain of Zeus, God of all the Greeks, you reach a sanctuary of Aphaea, in whose honor Pindar composed an ode for the Aeginetans. The Cretans say （the story of Aphaea is Cretan） that Carmanor, who purified Apollo alter he had killed <placeName key="tgn,7010770" authname="tgn,7010770">Pytho</placeName>, was the father of Lubulus, and that the daughter of Zeus and of Carme, the daughter of Eubulus, was Britomartis. She took delight, they say, in running and in the chase, and was very dear to Artemis. Fleeing from Minos, who had fallen in love with her, she threw herself into nets which had been cast （aphemena） for a draught of fishes. She was made a goddess by Artemis, and she is worshipped, not only by the Cretans, but also by the Aeginetans, who say that Britomartis shows herself in their island. Her surname among the Aeginetans is Aphaea; in <placeName key="tgn,7012056" authname="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName> it is Dictynna （Goddess of Nets）.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>The Mount of all the Greeks, except for the sanctuary of Zeus, has, I found, nothing else worthy of mention. This sanctuary, they say, was made for Zeus by Aeacus. The story of Auxesia and Damia, how the Epidaurians suffered from drought, how in obedience to an oracle they had these wooden images made of olive wood that they received from the Athenians, how the Epidaurians left off paying to the Athenians what they had agreed to pay, on the ground that the Aeginetans had the images, how the Athenians perished who crossed over to <placeName key="tgn,7011087" authname="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName> to fetch them—all this, as Herodotus<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hdt. 5.82" default="NO" valid="yes">Hdt. 5.82-87</bibl></note> has described it accurately and in detail, I have no intention of relating, because the story has been well told already; but I will add that I saw the images, and sacrificed to them in the same way as it is customary to sacrifice at <placeName key="perseus,Eleusis" authname="perseus,Eleusis">Eleusis</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>So much I must relate about <placeName key="tgn,7011087" authname="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName>, for the sake of Aeacus and his exploits. Bordering on Epidauria are the Troezenians, unrivalled glorifiers of their own country. They say that Orus was the first to be born in their land. Now, in my opinion, Orus is an Egyptian name and utterly un-Greek; but they assert that he became their king, and that the land was called Oraea after him and that Althepus, the son of Poseidon and of Leis, the daughter of Orus, inheriting the kingdom after Orus, named the land Althepia.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>During his reign, they say, Athena and Poseidon disputed about the land, and after disputing held it in common, as Zeus commanded them to do. For this reason they worship both Athena, whom they name both Polias （Urban） and Sthenias （Strong）, and also Poseidon, under the surname of King. And moreover their old coins have as device a trident and a face of Athena.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>After Althepus, Saron became king. They said that this man built the sanctuary for Saronian Artemis by a sea which is marshy and shallow, so that for this reason it was called the Phoebaean lagoon. Now Saron was very fond of hunting. As he was chasing a doe, it so chanced that it dashed into the sea and he dashed in alter it. The doe swam further and further from the shore, and Saron kept close to his prey, until his ardor brought him to the open ocean. Here his strength failed, and he was drowned in the waves. The body was cast ashore at the grove of Artemis by the Phoebaean lagoon, and they buried it within the sacred enclosure, and after him they named the sea in these parts the Saronic instead of the Phoebaean lagoon.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p>They know nothing of the later kings down to Hyperes and Anthas. These they assert to be sons of Poseidon and of Alcyone, daughter of Atlas, adding that they founded in the country the cities of Hyperea and <placeName key="perseus,Anthea" authname="perseus,Anthea">Anthea</placeName>; Aetius, however, the son of Anthas, on inheriting the kingdoms of his father and of his uncle, named one of the cities Poseidonias. When <placeName key="tgn,5004287" authname="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName> and Pittheus came to Aetius there were three kings instead of one, but the sons of Pelops enjoyed the balance of power.</p>
<milestone n="9" unit="section" /><p>Here is evidence of it. When <placeName key="tgn,5004287" authname="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName> died, Pittheus gathered the inhabitants together, incorporating both Hyperea and <placeName key="perseus,Anthea" authname="perseus,Anthea">Anthea</placeName> into the modern city, which he named <placeName key="tgn,5004287" authname="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName> after his brother. Many years afterwards the descendants of Aetius, son of Anthas, were dispatched as colonists from <placeName key="tgn,5004287" authname="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName>, and founded <placeName key="tgn,7016142" authname="tgn,7016142">Halicarnassus</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Myndus" authname="perseus,Myndus">Myndus</placeName> in <placeName key="tgn,7002358" authname="tgn,7002358">Caria</placeName>. Anaphlystus and Sphettus, sons of <placeName key="tgn,5004287" authname="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName>, migrated to <placeName key="tgn,7002681" authname="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>, and the parishes are named after them. As my readers know it already, I shall not relate the story of Theseus, the grandson of Pittheus. There is, however, one incident that I must add.</p>
<milestone n="10" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />On the return of the Heracleidae, the Troezenians too received Dorian settlers from <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>. They had been subject at even an earlier date to the Argives; Homer, too, in the Catalogue, says that their commander was Diomedes. For Diomedes and Euryalus, son of Mecisteus, who were guardians of the boy Cyanippus, son of Aegialeus, led the Argives to <placeName key="perseus,Troy" authname="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>. Sthenelus, as I have related above, came of a more illustrious family, called the Anaxagoridae, and he had the best claim to the Kingdom of <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>. Such is the story of the Troezenians, with the exception of the cities that claim to be their colonies. I will now proceed to describe the appointments of their sanctuaries and the remarkable sights of their country.</p>
<milestone n="31" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />In the market-place of <placeName key="tgn,5004287" authname="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName> is a temple of Artemis Saviour, with images of the goddess. It was said that the temple was founded and the name Saviour given by Theseus when he returned from <placeName key="tgn,7012056" authname="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName> after overcoming Asterion the son of Minos. This victory he considered the most noteworthy of his achievements, not so much, in my opinion, because Asterion was the bravest of those killed by Theseus, but because his success in unravelling the difficult Maze and in escaping unnoticed after the exploit made credible the saying that it was divine providence that brought Theseus and his company back in safety.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>In this temple are altars to the gods said to rule under the earth. It is here that they say Semele was brought out of Hell by Dionysus, and that Heracles dragged up the Hound of Hell.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Cerberus, the fabulous watch-dog.</note> But I cannot bring myself to believe even that Semele died at all, seeing that she was the wife of Zeus; while, as for the so-called Hound of Hell, I will give my views in another place.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Paus. 3.25.6" default="NO" valid="yes">Paus. 3.25.6</bibl>.</note></p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>Behind the temple is the tomb of Pittheus, on which are placed three seats of white marble. On them they say that Pittheus and two men with him used to sit in judgment. Not far off is a sanctuary of the Muses, made, they told me, by Ardalus, son of Hephaestus. This Ardalus they hold to have invented the flute, and after him they name the Muses Ardalides. Here, they say, Pittheus taught the art of rhetoric, and I have myself read a book purporting to be a treatise by Pittheus, published by a citizen of <placeName key="tgn,7011116" authname="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName>. Not far from the Muses' Hall is an old altar, which also, according to report, was dedicated by Ardalus. Upon it they sacrifice to the Muses and to Sleep, saying that Sleep is the god that is dearest to the Muses.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>Near the theater a temple of Artemis Lycea （Wolfish） was made by Hippolytus. About this surname I could learn nothing from the local guides, but I gathered that either Hippolytus destroyed wolves that were ravaging the land of <placeName key="tgn,5004287" authname="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName>, or else that Lycea is a surname of Artemis among the Amazons, from whom he was descended through his mother. Perhaps there may be another explanation that I am unaware of. The stone in front of the temple, called the Sacred Stone, they say is that on which nine men of <placeName key="tgn,5004287" authname="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName> once purified Orestes from the stain of matricide.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>Not far from Artemis Lycea are altars close to one another. The first of them is to Dionysus, surnamed, in accordance with an oracle, Saotes （Saviour）; the second is named the altar of the Themides （Laws）, and was dedicated, they say, by Pittheus. They had every reason, it seems to me, for making an altar to Helius Eleutherius （Sun, God of Freedom）, seeing that they escaped being enslaved by Xerxes and the Persians.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>The sanctuary of Thearian Apollo, they told me, was set up by Pittheus; it is the oldest I know of. Now the Phocaeans, too, in <placeName key="tgn,6002765" authname="tgn,6002765">Ionia</placeName> have an old temple of Athena, which was once burnt by Harpagus the Persian, and the Samians also have an old one of Pythian Apollo; these, however, were built much later than the sanctuary at <placeName key="tgn,5004287" authname="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName>. The modern image was dedicated by Auliscus, and made by Hermon of <placeName key="tgn,5004287" authname="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName>. This Hermon made also the wooden images of the Dioscuri.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>Under a portico in the market-place are set up women; both they and their children are of stone. They are the women and children whom the Athenians gave to the Troezenians to be kept safe, when they had resolved to evacuate <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and not to await the attack of the Persians by land. They are said to have dedicated likenesses, not of all the women—for, as a matter of fact, the statues are not many—but only of those who were of high rank.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p>In front of the sanctuary of Apollo is a building called the Booth of Orestes. For before he was cleansed for shedding his mother's blood, no citizen of <placeName key="tgn,5004287" authname="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName> would receive him into his home; so they lodged him here and gave him entertainment while they cleansed him, until they had finished the purification. Down to the present day the descendants of those who cleansed Orestes dine here on appointed days. A little way from the booth were buried, they say, the means of cleansing, and from them grew up a bay tree, which, indeed, still remains, being the one before this booth.</p>
<milestone n="9" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Among the means of cleansing which they say they used to cleanse Orestes was water from Hippocrene （Horse's Fount） for the Troezenians too have a fountain called the Horse's, and the legend about it does not differ from the one which prevails in <placeName key="tgn,7002683" authname="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName>. For they, too, say that the earth sent up the water when the horse Pegasus struck the ground with his hoof, and that Bellerophontes came to <placeName key="tgn,5004287" authname="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName> to ask Pittheus to give him Aethra to wife, but before the marriage took place he was banished from <placeName key="perseus,Corinth" authname="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="10" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Here there is also a Hermes called Polygius. Against this image, they say, Heracles leaned his club. Now this club, which was of wild olive, taking root in the earth （if anyone cares to believe the story）, grew up again and is still alive; Heracles, they say, discovering the wild olive by the Saronic Sea, cut a club from it. There is also a sanctuary of Zeus surnamed Saviour, which, they say, was made by Aetius, the son of Anthas, when he was king. To a water they give the name River of Gold. They say that when the land was afflicted with a drought for nine years, during which no rain fell, all the other waters dried up, but this River of Gold even then continued to flow as before.</p>
<milestone n="32" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />To Hippolytus, the son of Theseus, is devoted a very famous precinct, in which is a temple with an old image. Diomedes, they say, made these, and, moreover, was the first to sacrifice to Hippolytus. The Troezenians have a priest of Hippolytus, who holds his sacred office for life, and annual sacrifices have been established. They also observe the following custom. Every maiden before marriage cuts off a lock for Hippolytus, and, having cut it, she brings it to the temple and dedicates it. They will not have it that he was dragged to death by his horses, and, though they know his grave, they do not show it. But they believe that what is called the Charioteer in the sky is the Hippolytus of the legend, such being the honor he enjoys from the gods.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>Within this enclosure is a temple of Apollo Seafaring, an offering of Diomedes for having weathered the storm that came upon the Greeks as they were returning from <placeName key="tgn,7002329" authname="tgn,7002329">Troy</placeName>. They say that Diomedes was also the first to hold the Pythian games in honor of Apollo. Of Damia and Auxesia （for the Troezenians, too, share in their worship） they do not give the same account as the Epidaurians and Aeginetans, but say that they were maidens who came from <placeName key="tgn,7012056" authname="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>. A general insurrection having arisen in the city, these too, they say, were stoned to death by the opposite party; and they hold a festival in their honor that they call Stoning.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>In the other part of the enclosure is a race-course called that of Hippolytus, and above it a temple of Aphrodite Spy. For from here, whenever Hippolytus practised his exercises, Phaedra, who was in love with him, used to gaze upon him. Here there still grew the myrtle, with its leaves, as I have described above, pierced with holes. When Phaedra was in despair and could find no relief for her passion, she used to vent her spleen upon the leaves of this myrtle.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>There is also the grave of Phaedra, not far from the tomb of Hippolytus, which is a barrow near the myrtle. The image of Asclepius was made by Timotheus, but the Troezenians say that it is not Asclepius, but a likeness of Hippolytus. I remember, too, seeing the house of Hippolytus; before it is what is called the Fountain of Heracles, for Heracles, say the Troezenians, discovered the water.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>On the citadel is a temple of Athena, called Sthenias. The wooden image itself of the goddess I was made by CalIon, of <placeName key="tgn,7011087" authname="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName>.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">early fifth cent. B.C.</note> Callon was a pupil of Tectaeus and Angelion, who made the image of Apollo for the Delians. Angelion and Tectaeus were trained in the school of Dipoenus and Scyllis.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>On going down from here you come to a sanctuary of Pan Lyterius （Releasing）, so named because he showed to the Troezenian magistrates dreams which supplied a cure for the epidemic that had afflicted Troezenia, and the Athenians more than any other people. Having crossed the sanctuary, you can see a temple of Isis, and above it one of Aphrodite of the Height. The temple of Isis was made by the Halicarnassians in <placeName key="tgn,5004287" authname="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName>, because this is their mother-city, but the image of Isis was dedicated by the people of <placeName key="tgn,5004287" authname="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>On the road that leads through the mountains to <placeName key="perseus,Hermione" authname="perseus,Hermione">Hermione</placeName> is a spring of the river Hyllicus, originally called Taurius （Bull-like）, and a rock called the Rock of Theseus; when Theseus took up the boots and sword of Aegeus under it, it, too, changed its name, for before it was called the altar of Zeus Sthenius （Strong）. Near the rock is a sanctuary of Aphrodite Nymphia （Bridal）, made by Theseus when he took Helen to wife.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p>Outside the wall there is also a sanctuary of Poseidon Nurturer （Phytalmios）. For they say that, being wroth with them, Poseidon smote the land with barrenness, brine （halme） reaching the seeds and the roots of the plants （phyta）,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The epithet phytalmios means nourishing, but to judge from the story he gives, Pausanias must have connected it with the Greek words for brine and plant.</note> until, appeased by sacrifices and prayers, he ceased to send up the brine upon the earth. Above the temple of Poseidon is Demeter Lawbringer （Thesmophoros）, set up, they say, by Althepus.</p>
<milestone n="9" unit="section" /><p>On going down to the harbor at what is called Celenderis, you come to a place called Birthplace （Genethlion）, where Theseus is said to have been born. Before this place is a temple of Ares, for here also did Theseus conquer the Amazons in battle. These must have belonged to the army that strove in <placeName key="tgn,7002681" authname="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> against Theseus and the Athenians.</p>
<milestone n="10" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />As you make your way to the Psiphaean Sea you see a wild olive growing, which they call the Bent <term>Rhacos</term>. The Troezenians call <term>rhacos</term> every kind of barren olive—<term>cotinos</term>, <term>phylia</term>, or <term>elaios</term>—and this tree they call Bent because it was when the reins caught in it that the chariot of Hippolytus was upset. Not far from this stands the sanctuary of Saronian Artemis, and I have already given an account of it. I must add that every year they hold in honor of Artemis a festival called Saronia.</p>
<milestone n="33" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />The Troezenians possess islands, one of which is near the mainland, and it is possible to wade across the channel. This was formerly called Sphaeria, but its name was changed to Sacred Island for the following reason. In it is the tomb of Sphaerus, who, they say, was charioteer to Pelops. In obedience forsooth to a dream from Athena, Aethra crossed over into the island with libations for Sphaerus. After she had crossed, Poseidon is said to have had intercourse with her here. So for this reason Aethra set up here a temple of Athena Apaturia,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Apparently here derived from the Greek word for deceit.</note> and changed the name from Sphaeria to Sacred Island. She also established a custom for the Troezenian maidens of dedicating their girdles before wedlock to Athena Apaturia.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>Calaurea, they say, was sacred to Apollo of old, at the time when <placeName key="perseus,Delphi" authname="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName> was sacred to Poseidon. Legend adds that the two gods exchanged the two places. They still say this, and quote an oracle:—<quote type="oracle"><l met="dact"><placeName key="perseus,Delos" authname="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> and Calaurea alike thou lovest to dwell in,</l><l><placeName key="tgn,7010770" authname="tgn,7010770">Pytho</placeName>, too, the holy, and Taenarum swept by the high winds.</l></quote><bibl default="NO">Unknown</bibl>. At any rate, there is a holy sanctuary of Poseidon here, and it is served by a maiden priestess until she reaches an age fit for marriage.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>Within the enclosure is also the tomb of Demosthenes. His fate, and that of Homer before him, have, in my opinion, showed most plainly how spiteful the deity is; for Homer, after losing his sight, was, in addition to this great affliction, cursed with a second—a poverty which drove him in beggary to every land; while to Demosthenes it befell to experience exile in his old age and to meet with such a violent end. Now, although concerning him, not only others, but Demosthenes himself, have again and again declared that assuredly he took no part of the money that Harpalus brought from <placeName key="tgn,1000004" authname="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>,</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p>yet I must relate the circumstances of the statement made subsequently. Shortly after Harpalus ran away from <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and crossed with a squadron to <placeName key="tgn,7012056" authname="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>, he was put to death by the servants who were attending him, though some assert that he was assassinated by Pausanias, a Macedonian. The steward of his money fled to <placeName key="tgn,7011266" authname="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>, and was arrested by a Macedonian, Philoxenus, who also had demanded Harpalus from the Athenians. Having this slave in his power, he proceeded to examine him, until he learned everything about such as had allowed themselves to accept a bribe from Harpalus. On obtaining this information he sent a dispatch to <placeName key="perseus,Athens" authname="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>in which he gave a list of such as had taken a bribe from Harpalus, both their names and the sums each had received. Demosthenes, however, he never mentioned at all, although Alexander held him in bitter hatred, and he himself had a private quarrel with him.<milestone ed="P" unit="para" />So Demosthenes is honored in many parts of <placeName key="tgn,1000074" authname="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, and especially by the dwellers in Calaurea.</p>
<milestone n="34" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Stretching out far into the sea from Troezenia is a peninsula, on the coast of which has been founded a little town called <placeName key="perseus,Methana" authname="perseus,Methana">Methana</placeName>. Here there is a sanctuary of Isis, and on the market-place is an image of Hermes, and also one of Heracles. Some thirty stades distant from the town are hot baths. They say that it was when Antigonus, son of Demetrius, was king of <placeName key="tgn,7002715" authname="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName> that the water first appeared, and that what appeared at once was not water, but fire that gushed in great volume from the ground, and when this died down the water flowed; indeed, even at the present day it wells up hot and exceedingly salt. A bather here finds no cold water at hand, and if he dives into the sea his swim is full of danger. For wild creatures live in it, and it swarms with sharks.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>I will also relate what astonished me most in <placeName key="perseus,Methana" authname="perseus,Methana">Methana</placeName>. The wind called Lips,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">A S.W. wind.</note> striking the budding vines from the Saronic Gulf, blights their buds. So while the wind is still rushing on, two men cut in two a cock whose feathers are all white, and run round the vines in opposite directions, each carrying half of the cock. When they meet at their starting place, they bury the pieces there.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>Such are the means they have devised against the Lips. The islets, nine in number, lying off the land are called the Isles of Pelops, and they say that when it rains one of them is not touched. If this be the case I do not know, though the people around <placeName key="perseus,Methana" authname="perseus,Methana">Methana</placeName> said that it was true, and I have seen before now men trying to keep off hail by sacrifices and spells.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" /><placeName key="perseus,Methana" authname="perseus,Methana">Methana</placeName>, then, is a peninsula of the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>. Within it, bordering on the land of <placeName key="tgn,5004287" authname="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName>, is <placeName key="perseus,Hermione" authname="perseus,Hermione">Hermione</placeName>. The founder of the old city, the Hermionians say, was <placeName key="tgn,5004284" authname="tgn,5004284">Hermion</placeName>, the son of Europs. Now Europs, whose father was certainly Phoroneus, Herophanes of <placeName key="tgn,5004287" authname="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName> said was an illegitimate child. For surely the kingdom of <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> would never have devolved upon Argus, Niobe's son, the grandchild of Phoroneus, in the presence of a legitimate son.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>But even supposing that Europs was a legitimate child who died before Phoroneus, I am quite sure that his son was not likely to stand a fair chance against Niobe's child, whose father was supposed to be Zeus. Subsequently the Dorians from <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> settled, among other places, at <placeName key="tgn,5004284" authname="tgn,5004284">Hermion</placeName>, but I do not think there was war between the two peoples, or it would have been spoken of by the Argives.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />There is a road from <placeName key="tgn,5004287" authname="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName> to <placeName key="tgn,5004284" authname="tgn,5004284">Hermion</placeName> by way of the rock which aforetime was called the altar of Zeus Sthenius （Strong） but afterwards Theseus<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See <bibl n="Paus. 1.27." default="NO" valid="yes">Paus. 1.27.8</bibl>, and <bibl n="Paus. 2.32.7" default="NO" valid="yes">Paus. 2.32.7</bibl>.</note> took up the tokens, and people now call it the Rock of Theseus. As you go, then, along a mountain road by way of this rock, you reach a temple of Apollo surnamed Platanistius （God of the Plane-tree Grove）, and a place called Eilei, where are sanctuaries of Demeter and of her daughter Core （Maid）. Seawards, on the borders of Hermionis, is a sanctuary of Demeter surnamed Thermasia （Warmth）.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>Just about eighty stades away is a headland Scyllaeum, which is named alter the daughter of Nisus. For when, owing to her treachery,<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See <bibl n="Paus. 1.19" default="NO" valid="yes">Paus. 1.19</bibl>.</note> Minos had taken <placeName key="perseus,Nisaea" authname="perseus,Nisaea">Nisaea</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Megara" authname="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName>, he said that now he would not have her to wife, and ordered his Cretans to throw her from the ship. She was drowned, and the waves cast up her body on this headland. They do not show a grave of her, but say that the sea birds were allowed to tear the corpse to pieces.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p>As you sail from Scyllaeum in the direction of the city, you reach another headland, called Bucephala （Ox-head）, and, after the headland, islands, the first of which is Haliussa （Salt Island）. This provides a harbor where there is good anchorage. After it comes <placeName key="tgn,7002579" authname="tgn,7002579">Pityussa</placeName> （<placeName key="tgn,2582768" authname="tgn,2582768">Pine Island</placeName>）, and the third they call Aristerae. On sailing past these you come to another headland, Colyergia, jutting out from the mainland, and after it to an island, called Tricrana （Three Heads）, and a mountain, projecting into the sea from the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>, called Buporthmus （<placeName key="tgn,7011931" authname="tgn,7011931">Oxford</placeName>）. On Buporthmus has been built a sanctuary of Demeter and her daughter, as well as one of Athena, surnamed Promachorma （Champion of the Anchorage）.</p>
<milestone n="9" unit="section" /><p>Before Buporthmus lies an island called Aperopia, not far from which is another island, Hydrea. After it the mainland is skirted by a crescent-shaped beach and after the beach there is a spit of land up to a sanctuary of Poseidon, beginning at the sea on the east and extending westwards.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">i.e. the spit runs eastward into the sea from the west.</note> It possesses harbors, and is some seven stades in length, and not more than three stades in breadth where it is broadest.</p>
<milestone n="10" unit="section" /><p>Here the Hermionians had their former city. They still have sanctuaries here: one of Poseidon at the east end of the spit, and a temple of Athena further inland by the side of the latter are the foundations of a race-course, in which legend says the sons of Tyndareus contended. There is also another sanctuary of Athena, of no great size, the roof of which has fallen in. There is a temple to Helius （Sun）, another to the Graces, and a third to Serapis and Isis. There are also circuits of large unhewn stones, within which they perform mystic ritual to Demeter.</p>
<milestone n="11" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Such are the possessions of the Hermionians in these parts. The modern city is just about four stades distant from the headland, upon which is the sanctuary of Poseidon, and it lies on a site which is level at first, gently rising up a slope, which presently merges into Pron, for so they name this mountain. A wall stands all round <placeName key="perseus,Hermione" authname="perseus,Hermione">Hermione</placeName>, a city which I found afforded much to write about, and among the things which I thought I myself must certainly mention are a temple of Aphrodite, surnamed both <placeName key="tgn,7006720" authname="tgn,7006720">Pontia</placeName> （of the Deep Sea） and <placeName key="tgn,5000700" authname="tgn,5000700">Limenia</placeName> （of the Harbor）, and a white-marble image of huge size, and worth seeing for its artistic excellence.</p>
<milestone n="12" unit="section" /><p>There is also another temple of Aphrodite. Among the honors paid her by the Hermionians is this custom: maidens, and widows about to remarry, all sacrifice to her before wedding. Sanctuaries have also been built of Demeter Thermasia （Warmth）, one at the border towards Troezenia, as I have stated above, while there is another in <placeName key="perseus,Hermione" authname="perseus,Hermione">Hermione</placeName> itself.</p>
<milestone n="35" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Near the latter is a temple of Dionysus of the Black Goatskin. In his honor every year they hold a competition in music, and they offer prizes for swimming-races and boat-races. There is also a sanctuary of Artemis surnamed Iphigenia, and a bronze Poseidon with one foot upon a dolphin. Passing by this into the sanctuary of Hestia, we see no image, but only an altar, and they sacrifice to Hestia upon it.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>Of Apollo there are three temples and three images. One has no surname; the second they call Pythaeus, and the third Horius （of the Borders）. The name Pythaeus they have learned from the Argives, for Telesilla<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">See <bibl n="Paus. 2.20.8" default="NO" valid="yes">Paus. 2.20.8</bibl>.</note> tells us that they were the first Greeks to whose country came Pythaeus, who was a son of Apollo. I cannot say for certain why they call the third Horius, but I conjecture that they won a victory, either in war or by arbitration, in a dispute concerning the borders （horoi） of their land, and for this reason paid honors to Apollo Horius.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>The sanctuary of Fortune is said by the Hermionians to be the newest in their city; a colossus of Parian marble stands there. Of their wells, one is very old; nobody can see the water flowing into it, but it would never run dry, even if everybody descended and drew water from it. Another well they made in our own day, and the name of the place from which the water flows into it is Leimon （Meadow）.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />The object most worthy of mention is a sanctuary of Demeter on Pron. This sanctuary is said by the Hermionians to have been founded by Clymenus, son of Phoroneus, and Chthonia, sister of Clymenus. But the <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> account is that when Demeter came to <placeName key="tgn,7002739" authname="tgn,7002739">Argolis</placeName>, while Atheras and Mysius afforded hospitality to the goddess, Colontas neither received her into his home nor paid her any other mark of respect. His daughter Chthoia disapproved of this conduct. They say that Colontas was punished by being burnt up along with his house, while Chthonia was brought to <placeName key="tgn,5004284" authname="tgn,5004284">Hermion</placeName> by Demeter, and made the sanctuary for the Hermionians.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>At any rate, the goddess herself is called Chthonia, and Chthonia is the name of the festival they hold in the summer of every year. The manner of it is this. The procession is headed by the priests of the gods and by all those who hold the annual magistracies; these are followed by both men and women. It is now a custom that some who are still children should honor the goddess in the procession. These are dressed in white, and wear wreaths upon their heads. Their wreaths are woven of the flower called by the natives <term>cosmosandalon</term>, which, from its size and color, seems to me to be an iris; it even has inscribed upon it the same letters of mourning.<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">The letters AI, an exclamation of woe supposed to be inscribed on the flower.</note></p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>Those who form the procession are followed by men leading from the herd a full-grown cow, fastened with ropes, and still untamed and frisky. Having driven the cow to the temple, some loose her from the ropes that she may rush into the sanctuary, others, who hitherto have been holding the doors open, when they see the cow within the temple, close the doors.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>Four old women, left behind inside, are they who dispatch the cow. Whichever gets the chance cuts the throat of the cow with a sickle. Afterwards the doors are opened, and those who are appointed drive up a second cow, and a third after that, and yet a fourth. All are dispatched in the same way by the old women, and the sacrifice has yet another strange feature. On whichever of her sides the first cow falls, all the others must fall on the same.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p>Such is the manner in which the sacrifice is performed by the Hermionians. Before the temple stand a few statues of the women who have served Demeter as her priestess, and on passing inside you see seats on which the old women wait for the cows to be driven in one by one, and images, of no great age, of Athena and Demeter. But the thing itself that they worship more than all else, I never saw, nor yet has any other man, whether stranger or Hermionian. The old women may keep their knowledge of its nature to themselves.</p>
<milestone n="9" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />There is also another temple, all round which stand statues. This temple is right opposite that of Chthonia, and is called that of Clymenus, and they sacrifice to Clymenus here. I do not believe that Clymenus was an Argive who came to Hermion “Clymenus” is the surname of the god, whoever legend says is king in the underworld.</p>
<milestone n="10" unit="section" /><p>Beside this temple is another; it is of Ares, and has an image of the god, while to the right of the sanctuary of Chthonia is a portico, called by the natives the Portico of Echo. It is such that if a man speaks it reverberates at least three times. Behind the temple of Chthonia are three places which the Hermionians call that of Clymenus, that of Pluto, and the Acherusian Lake. All are surrounded by fences of stones, while in the place of Clymenus there is also a chasm in the earth. Through this, according to the legend of the Hermionians, Heracles brought up the Hound of Hell.</p>
<milestone n="11" unit="section" /><p>At the gate through which there is a straight road leading to <placeName key="perseus,Mases" authname="perseus,Mases">Mases</placeName>, there is a sanctuary of Eileithyia within the wall. Every day, both with sacrifices and with incense, they magnificently propitiate the goddess, and, moreover, there is a vast number of votive gifts offered to Eileithyia. But the image no one may see, except, perhaps, the priestesses.</p>
<milestone n="36" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Proceeding about seven stades along the straight road to <placeName key="perseus,Mases" authname="perseus,Mases">Mases</placeName>, you reach, on turning to the left, a road to Halice. At the present day Halice is deserted, but once it, too, had inhabitants, and there is mention made of citizens of Halice on the Epidaurian slabs on which are inscribed the cures of Asclepius. I know, however, no other authentic document in which mention is made either of the city Halice or of its citizens. Well, to this city also there is a road, which lies midway between Pron and another mountain, called in old days Thornax; but they say that the name was changed because, according to legend, it was here that the transformation of Zeus into a cuckoo took place.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>Even to the present day there are sanctuaries on the tops of the mountains: on Mount Cuckoo one of Zeus, on Pron one of Hera. At the foot of Mount Cuckoo is a temple, but there are no doors standing, and I found it without a roof or an image inside. The temple was said to be Apollo's. by the side of it runs a road to <placeName key="perseus,Mases" authname="perseus,Mases">Mases</placeName> for those who have turned aside from the straight road. <placeName key="perseus,Mases" authname="perseus,Mases">Mases</placeName> was in old days a city, even as Homer<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><bibl n="Hom. Il. 2.562" default="NO" valid="yes">Hom. Il. 2.562</bibl></note> represents it in the catalogue of the Argives, but in my time the Hermionians were using it as a seaport.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>From <placeName key="perseus,Mases" authname="perseus,Mases">Mases</placeName> there is a road on the right to a headland called Struthus （Sparrow Peak）. From this headland by way of the summits of the mountains the distance to the place called Philanorium and to the Boleoi is two hundred and fifty stades. These Boleoi are heaps of unhewn stones. Another place, called Twins, is twenty stades distant from here. There is here a sanctuary of Apollo, a sanctuary of Poseidon, and in addition one of Demeter. The images are of white marble, and are upright.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Next comes a district, belonging to the Argives, that once was called Asinaea, and by the sea are ruins of <placeName key="perseus,Asine" authname="perseus,Asine">Asine</placeName>. When the Lacedaemonians and their king Nicander, son of Charillus, son of Polydectes, son of Eunomus, son of Prytanis, son of Eurypon, invaded <placeName key="tgn,7002739" authname="tgn,7002739">Argolis</placeName> with an army, the Asinaeans joined in the invasion, and with them ravaged the land of the Argives. When the Lacedaemonian expedition departed home, the Argives under their king Eratus attacked <placeName key="perseus,Asine" authname="perseus,Asine">Asine</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>For a time the Asinaeans defended themselves from their wall, and killed among others Lysistratus, one of the most notable men of <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>. But when the wall was lost, the citizens put their wives and children on board their vessels and abandoned their own country; the Argives, while levelling <placeName key="perseus,Asine" authname="perseus,Asine">Asine</placeName> to the ground and annexing its territory to their own, left the sanctuary of Apollo Pythaeus, which is still visible, and by it they buried Lysistratus.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />Distant from <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> forty stades and no more is the sea at <placeName key="perseus,Lerna" authname="perseus,Lerna">Lerna</placeName>. On the way down to <placeName key="perseus,Lerna" authname="perseus,Lerna">Lerna</placeName> the first thing on the road is the Erasinus, which empties itself into the Phrixus, and the Phrixus into the sea between <placeName key="perseus,Temenium" authname="perseus,Temenium">Temenium</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Lerna" authname="perseus,Lerna">Lerna</placeName>. About eight stades to the left from the Erasinus is a sanctuary of the Lords Dioscuri （Sons of Zeus）. Their wooden images have been made similar to those in the city.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>On returning to the straight road, you will cross the Erasinus and reach the river Cheimarrus （Winter-torrent）. Near it is a circuit of stones, and they say that Pluto, after carrying off, according to the story, Core, the daughter of Demeter, descended here to his fabled kingdom underground. <placeName key="perseus,Lerna" authname="perseus,Lerna">Lerna</placeName> is, I have already stated, by the sea, and here they celebrate mysteries in honor of Lernaean Demeter.</p>
<milestone n="8" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />There is a sacred grove beginning on the mountain they call Pontinus. Now Mount Pontinus does not let the rain-water flow away, but absorbs it into itself. From it flows a river, also called Pontinus. Upon the top of the mountain is a sanctuary of Athena Saitis, now merely a ruin; there are also the foundations of a house of Hippomedon, who went to <placeName key="perseus,Thebes" authname="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> to redress the wrongs of Polyneices, son of Oedipus.</p>
<milestone n="37" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />At this mountain begins the grove, which consists chiefly of plane trees, and reaches down to the sea. Its boundaries are, on the one side the river Pantinus, on the other side another river, called Amymane, after the daughter of Danaus. Within the grave are images of Demeter Prosymne and of Dionysus. Of Demeter there is a seated image of no great size.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>Both are of stone, but in another temple is a seated wooden image of Dionysus Saotes （Savior）, while by the sea is a stone image of Aphrodite. They say that the daughters of Danaus dedicated it, while Danaus himself made the sanctuary of Athena by the Pontinus. The mysteries of the Lernaeans were established, they say, by Philammon. Now the words which accompany the ritual are evidently of no antiquity</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>and the inscription also, which I have heard is written on the heart made of orichalcum, was shown not to be Philammon's by Arriphon, an Aetolian of Triconium by descent, who now enjoys a reputation second to none among the Lycians; excellent at original research, he found the clue to this problem in the following way: the verses, and the prose interspersed among the verses, are all written in Doric. But before the return of the Heracleidae to the <placeName key="tgn,7017076" authname="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName> the Argives spoke the same dialect as the Athenians, and in Philammon's day I do not suppose that even the name Dorians was familiar to all Greek ears.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />All this was proved in the demonstration. At the source of the Amymone grows a plane tree, beneath which, they say, the hydra （water-snake） grew. I am ready to believe that this beast was superior in size to other water-snakes, and that its poison had something in it so deadly that Heracles treated the points of his arrows with its gall. It had, however, in my opinion, one head, and not several. It was Peisander<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified">Peisander wrote a poem on the labors of Heracles. His date is uncertain, but perhaps he flourished about <date value="-645" authname="-645">645 B.C.</date></note> of Camirus who, in order that the beast might appear more frightful and his poetry might be more remarkable, represented the hydra with its many heads.</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>I saw also what is called the Spring of Amphiaraus and the Alcyonian Lake, through which the Argives say Dionysus went down to Hell to bring up Semele, adding that the descent here was shown him by Palymnus. There is no limit to the depth of the Alcyonian Lake, and I know of nobody who by any contrivance has been able to reach the bottom of it since not even Nero, who had ropes made several stades long and fastened them together, tying lead to them, and omitting nothing that might help his experiment, was able to discover any limit to its depth.</p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>This, too, I heard. The water of the lake is, to all appearance, calm and quiet but, although it is such to look at, every swimmer who ventures to cross it is dragged down, sucked into the depths, and swept away. The circumference of the lake is not great, being about one-third of a stade. Upon its banks grow grass and rushes. The nocturnal rites performed every year in honor of Dionysus I must not divulge to the world at large.</p>
<milestone n="38" unit="chapter" /><milestone n="1" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" /><placeName key="perseus,Temenium" authname="perseus,Temenium">Temenium</placeName> is in <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> territory, and was named after Temenus, the son of Aristomachus. For, having seized and strengthened the position, he waged therefrom with the Dorians the war against Tisamenus and the Achaeans. On the way to <placeName key="perseus,Temenium" authname="perseus,Temenium">Temenium</placeName> from <placeName key="perseus,Lerna" authname="perseus,Lerna">Lerna</placeName> the river Phrixus empties itself into the sea, and in <placeName key="perseus,Temenium" authname="perseus,Temenium">Temenium</placeName> is built a sanctuary of Poseidon, as well as one of Aphrodite; there is also the tomb of Temenus, which is worshipped by the Dorians in <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>.</p>
<milestone n="2" unit="section" /><p>Fifty stades, I conjecture, from <placeName key="perseus,Temenium" authname="perseus,Temenium">Temenium</placeName> is <placeName key="tgn,7011013" authname="tgn,7011013">Nauplia</placeName>, which at the present day is uninhabited; its founder was Nauplius, reputed to be a son of Poseidon and Amymone. Of the walls, too, ruins still remain and in <placeName key="tgn,7011013" authname="tgn,7011013">Nauplia</placeName> are a sanctuary of Poseidon, harbors, and a spring called Canathus. Here, say the Argives, Hera bathes every year and recovers her maidenhood.</p>
<milestone n="3" unit="section" /><p>This is one of the sayings told as a holy secret at the mysteries which they celebrate in honor of Hera. The story told by the people in <placeName key="tgn,7011013" authname="tgn,7011013">Nauplia</placeName> about the ass, how by nibbling down the shoots of a vine he caused a more plenteous crop of grapes in the future, and how for this reason they have carved an ass on a rock, because he taught the pruning of vines—all this I pass over as trivial.</p>
<milestone n="4" unit="section" /><p><milestone ed="P" unit="para" />From <placeName key="perseus,Lerna" authname="perseus,Lerna">Lerna</placeName> there is also another road, which skirts the sea and leads to a place called Genesium. By the sea is a small sanctuary of Poseidon Genesius. Next to this is another place, called <placeName key="perseus,Apobathmi" authname="perseus,Apobathmi">Apobathmi</placeName> （Steps）. The story is that this is the first place in <placeName key="tgn,7002739" authname="tgn,7002739">Argolis</placeName> where Danaus landed with his daughters. From here we pass through what is called Anigraea, along a narrow and difficult road, until we reach a tract on the left which stretches down to the sea;</p>
<milestone n="5" unit="section" /><p>it is fertile in trees, especially the olive. As you go up inland from this is a place where three hundred picked Argives fought for this land with an equal number of specially chosen Lacedaemonian warriors<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><date value="-548" authname="-548">548 B.C.</date></note>. All were killed except one Spartan and two Argives, and here were raised the graves for the dead. But the Lacedaemonians, having fought against the Argives with all their forces, won a decisive victory; at first they themselves enjoyed the fruits of the land, but afterwards they assigned it to the Aeginetans, when they were expelled from their island by the Athenians<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><date value="-431" authname="-431">431 B.C.</date></note>. In my time Thyreatis was inhabited by the Argives, who say that they recovered it by the award of an arbitration<note anchored="yes" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"><date value="-338" authname="-338">338 B.C.</date></note></p>
<milestone n="6" unit="section" /><p>As you go from these common graves you come to Athene, where Aeginetans once made their home, another village <placeName key="tgn,1131479" authname="tgn,1131479">Neris</placeName>, and a third Eua, the largest of the villages, in which there is a sanctuary of Polemocrates. This Polemocrates is one of the sons of Machaon, and the brother of Alexanor; he cures the people of the district, and receives honors from the neighbours.</p>
<milestone n="7" unit="section" /><p>Above the villages extends Mount Parnon, on which the Lacedaemonian border meets the borders of the Argives and Tegeatae. On the borders stand stone figures of Hermes, from which the name of the place is derived. A river called Tanaus, which is the only one descending from Mount Parnon, flows through the <placeName key="tgn,5001993" authname="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> territory and empties itself into the Gulf of Thyrea.</p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>